<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Primitive Christianity continued in the faith and practice of the people called Quakers being in answer to a pamphlet entituled, Primitive heresie &amp;c. and which may serve as an appendix to a book entituled, An antidote against the venom of the snake in the grass, by George Whitehead / Joseph Wyeth.</title>
            <author>Wyeth, Joseph, 1663-1731.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 125 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 38 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67211</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3761</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R27627</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09985603</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09985603</idno>
            <idno type="VID">44459</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67211)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 44459)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1371:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Primitive Christianity continued in the faith and practice of the people called Quakers being in answer to a pamphlet entituled, Primitive heresie &amp;c. and which may serve as an appendix to a book entituled, An antidote against the venom of the snake in the grass, by George Whitehead / Joseph Wyeth.</title>
                  <author>Wyeth, Joseph, 1663-1731.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 58, [8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and sold by T. Sowle,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Primitive heresie.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:44459:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Primitive Chriſtianity</hi> CONTINUED, IN THE Faith and Practice Of the PEOPLE called QUAKERS: BEING IN ANSVVER To a Pamphlet, Entituled, <hi>Primitive Hereſie,</hi> &amp;c. And which may ſerve as an <hi>Appendix</hi> to a Book, Entituled, <hi>An Antidote againſt the Venom of the Snake in the Graſs,</hi> by <hi>George Whitehead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Joſeph Wyeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Prov. 24. 8.</bibl> 
               <hi>He that Deviſeth to do Evil, ſhall be called a Miſchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous Perſon.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Pſal. 140. 3.</bibl> 
               <hi>They have ſharpened their Tongues like a Serpent: Adders Poiſon is under their Lips.</hi> Selah.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed and Sold by <hi>T. Sowle,</hi> next Door to the <hi>Meeting-Houſe</hi> in <hi>White-Hart-Court</hi> in <hi>Gracieus-ſtreet,</hi> and at the <hi>Bible</hi> in <hi>Leaden-hall-ſtreet</hi> near the <hi>Market,</hi> 1698.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:44459:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:44459:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Friendly Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>THE Enſuing Leaves, which contain our Vindication a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Black Attempts of a Neceſſitous and Malicious Prieſt, in a Piece of his, Emtituled,</hi> Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Hereſie, <hi>&amp;c. are Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to thy Peruſal; wherein thou wilt ſee the Conſonancy and Conſtancy of our Principles to the Holy Scriptures Aſſerted, in Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to the Charges of Hereſie, and New Repreſentation by him Falſly, but not firſt laid: For it</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:44459:3"/> 
               <hi>hath often been the Practice of our Adverſaries, when we have brought forth our True Teſtimonies, to ſay, our Repreſentation was New.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But, as this Man ſeems to Love Controverſie, in Oppoſition to Peace and Quiet, becauſe he may find his Bread or Baſe Ends ſupplied by the Conteſt; and to make uſe of Falſe Gloſſes to Colour the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Occaſion: So I Eſteem it a Duty to wipe off the Dirt he hath flung at us herein; for which, though I have none of his mean Profits; yet I can aſſure thee,</hi> Reader, <hi>I have Satisfaction in ſo doing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Method I have herein ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken is this, I have from the Year</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:44459:3"/> 55. <hi>or there about, brought in a Succeſſion, divers Teſtimonies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Particular Charges; which do at once ſhew, that what we now Profeſs, is no other than what we did: The Quotations all ſpeak the Minds of the Perſons, whoſe Names they bear: I ſay this, becauſe thoſe Quotations of our Friends, which this Man brings, does not, nor can, after the Barbarity he hath uſed toward them, of which I have herein given divers Inſtances.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I need Preface no further, than to Acquaint thee, that as the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor Stiles himſelf from the</hi> Snake in the Graſs, <hi>I alſo have frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Stiled him ſo; not being willing</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:44459:4"/> 
               <hi>to Abridge him a Title of his own chooſing, which fitly Expreſſes the Workings of that Deceit, which was firſt began by the great Enemy of Man, the</hi> Devil; <hi>from whoſe Temptations and all Deceit, howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever working; The Spirit of Truth, which comes by</hi> Jeſus Chriſt <hi>can only be thy Safe Guide: To this thou art in all Sincerity Commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:44459:4"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>I. <hi>THE Incarnation of Chriſt; that is, the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion of the Divine and Humane Natures, in his being made Fleſh, Aſſerted and Believed.</hi> p. 12</item>
               <item>II. <hi>The Truth and Reality of his Death and Sufferings, Aſſerted and Believed.</hi> p. 19</item>
               <item>III. <hi>The Reſurrection and Future Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Believed and Teſtified to.</hi> p. 25</item>
               <item>IV.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Baptiſm and the Supper ſpoken to.</hi> p. 32.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Marriage owned, and Fornication Preached down and denied.</hi> p. 39</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>V.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Magiſtracy and Government owned.</hi> p. 46</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>No Stiffneſs in not taking off Hats: Civility acknowledged to all.</hi> p. 48</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:44459:5"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Concluſion.</hi> p. 49</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Miſrepreſentation fixed.</hi> p. 51</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Our Ancient Belief, no Modern Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation.</hi> p. 53</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Expoſtulation with</hi> W. Penn <hi>Conſidered.</hi> ibid.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:44459:5"/>
            <head>Primitive Chriſtianity <hi>CONTINUED,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECT. I.</head>
               <p>LOVE to Truth, not Controverſie, hath drawn this from me; for from a well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grounded Satisfaction, Knowledge and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief (according to my meaſure) in the Manifeſted Principles of True Religion, I could with more eaſe have been pleaſed to Injoy that quiet which reſults from the Practice of them; and which it hath Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Government to allow to Perſons quictly, tho' differently Opining. To the Diſturbance of the Quiet, thus allowed, there hath of late appeared an Expulſed <hi>Clergy-man,</hi> boaſting himſelf to be ſome great one, and indeed in all the Qualities of Venom, Slander and Abuſe he is ſo, his firſt (for what I know) Libel againſt us, <hi>The Snake in the Graſs,</hi> ſhews this; and this he makes the Epoch of his Scanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Practice in his ſucceeding Scurrilous Pamphlets, which his Sculking Leiſure and Malice Furniſhes him with Opportunity to multiply; for, from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an Expulſed Prieſt, he makes it a Trade for Bread, and in part to repair thoſe Loſſes which he charges the preſent Eſtabliſhment to have brought upon him: What he ſays of himſelf is, That he Fights for his Soul, the <hi>Joy and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion of</hi> Chriſtendom, <hi>the Honour of Religion, and</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pri. Her.</hi> p. 20.</note> 
                  <hi>the Glory of God.</hi> But upon better Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation this appears to be Falſe, and that
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:44459:6"/> he ſeeks nothing leſs than thoſe good things he ſpeaks of, but to varniſh ill Attempts with Specious Titles, and the Confuſion of a Church and Nation, with a Prayer <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Diſ.</hi> Shewing who they are that are now qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> p. 33.</note> for a <hi>Removal of High Places</hi> is no new thing. But to come more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly to his Out-rage againſt us: He is pleaſed to Charge us with Follies, Crimes, Errors and Hereſies of very many ſorts; and herein hath gone ſo far, that, I think, there are few that know and impartially conſider us, but know that it is Falſe, though Atteſted, <hi>Verbo ſacerdotis,</hi> in the diſguiſe of a <hi>Snake,</hi> &amp;c. It is true, it is no new thing for particular Perſons or Communities of Men to be Charged with Blackeſt Crimes, Greateſt Errors, Schiſms and Hereſies. An Inſtance of this kind, and which comes to our preſent purpoſe, is ſeen in the <hi>Apology</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> for her ſeparation from <hi>Rome;</hi> in the Fifth Article there is numbred up ſome of the Crimes which were Charged upon her; the Article it ſelf follows:</p>
               <p>
                  <q> Clamant hodie paſſim nos omnes eſſe haereticos, diſccſſiſſe à ſide &amp; novis perſuaſionibus atque impiis dogmatis, Eccleſiae cauſam diſſipaviſſe: nos veteres &amp; jam <note place="margin">Doctrina &amp; Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia Eccleſiae An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glicanae, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> p. 3. <hi>Ar.</hi> 5.</note> olim Damnatas Haereſes ab inferis redivivas reſtituere, &amp; novas ſectas &amp; inauditos furores diſſeminare: jam etiam in contrarias factiones &amp; ſententias di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractos eſſe, nec ullo pacto potuiſſe unquam inter nos ipſos convenire: eſſe homines &amp; gigantum more, Deo ipſe bellum facere, &amp; prorſus ſine omni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>numinis cura, cultuque vivere: nos omnia recte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>facta deſpicere, non virtutis diſciplina uti ulla,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:44459:6"/> non legibus, non moribus, non jus, non aequum, non rectum colere; ad omnia flagitia laxare fraenoe, &amp; populum ad omni genus licentiae atque libidinis provocare: nos id agere &amp; querere, ut monarchiae &amp; regnorum ſtatus evertantur, &amp; omnia ad popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larem temeritatem, &amp; imperitae multitudinis do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minationem ridigantur: nos ab Eccleſiae Catholicae tumultuoſe defeciſſe, &amp; nefario Schiſmate orbem terrarum concuſſiſſe, &amp; pacem communem, at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> otium Eccleſiae publicum conturbaſſe: ut<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> olim <hi>Dathan</hi> &amp; <hi>Abiram Arone</hi> &amp; <hi>Moſe,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Num. 16.</note> ita nos hodie à Romano Pontifice, ſine ulla ſatis juſta cauſa ſeceſſionem feciſſe; priſcorum Patrum &amp; veterum conciliorum anctoritatem pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nihilo putare: Caeremonias antiquas à patribus &amp; proavis noſtris multis jam Seculis, bonis moribus, &amp; melioribus temporis approbatus, temerè &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolenter abrogaſſe; &amp; noſtra tantum privata ancto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritate, injuſſu ſacri &amp; Ocumenici conſilii, novos in Eccleſiam ritus invexiſſe: at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> iſta nos omnia non Religionis causa, ſed contention is tantùm ſtudio feciſſe. Se autem nihil prorſus immutaſſe, omnia vero ut ab Apoſtolis tradita, &amp; ab antiquiſſimis Patribus approbata fuerint, ad hunc uſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> diem per tot ſecula retinuiſſe. </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>They cry every where this day, We are all Hereticks, departed from the Faith, have rent the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Church with now and ungodly Tents, that we have Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vived and Reſtored the old Damned Hereſies, have ſown new and unheard of Sects and Madneſſes, and are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready broke into Factions and Diviſions, nor by any agreement can never be united among our ſelves: Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious Men of monſtrous Manners, making War againſt God, and living without all Worſhip and Fear of the Godhead: That we deſpiſed every right Way, and uſed</hi>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:44459:7"/> 
                  <hi>no Virtuous Diſcipline, nor loved either Laws, Manners, Religion, Right or Equity, but let looſe the Rein to all manner of Wickedneſs, and Provoked the People to every kind of Licentiouſneſs and Luſt, and ſought and did this that the State of Kingdoms and Monarchies might be over-turned and reduced under the Rule of the Raſh and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nskilful Multitude: That we have Tumultuouſly Separated from the</hi> Catholick Church, <hi>and have ſhook the Earth with a Nefarious Schiſm, and have troubled the common Peace and Quiet of the Church, and as</hi> Dathan <hi>and</hi> Abiram <hi>from</hi> Aaron <hi>and</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Num. 16.</note> Moſes, <hi>ſo we this day from the High Prieſt have made ſeparation without any cauſe ſufficiently juſt: That we account for nothing the Authority of the Ancient Fathers and Old Counſels, that we have raſhly and inſolently Abrogated the Ancient Ceremonies and Good Manners which by or Fathers and Fore-fathers for many Ages were Approved; and only by our private Authority have brought new Rites into the Church, no Holy and Ocu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menick Counſel Commanding; and that we have done all theſe things, not for the cauſe of Religion but only in a Study of Contention: But that ſhe is not all chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but that all things, as delivered by the Apoſtles, and as they have been Approved by the Ancient Fathers, do through ſo many Ages remain to this very day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This, with much more in the Apology, is ſaid to have been the Charge of <hi>Rome,</hi> and yet, I do not doubt but this Man will readily diſcharge Her from theſe theſe alledged Crimes. Hence we may have at leaſt this Conſolation, That we are not therefore Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanouſly Criminal, becauſe Villanouſly Charged; and to ſhew that we are not ſo, there hath been already Publiſhed an Anſwer to that Venomous Piece of Villanny, <hi>The Snake in the Graſs;</hi> wherein is alſo
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:44459:7"/> ome notice taken, and anſwer made to ſome noted Paſſages in two other Scandalous Pamphlets, one Entituled, <hi>Satan Diſrob'd,</hi> &amp;c. and the other, <hi>A Diſcourſe for Water-Baptiſm,</hi> &amp;c. which Anſwer is Entituled, <hi>An Antidote againſt the Venom of the Snake,</hi> &amp;c. by <hi>George Whitehead;</hi> in which Anſwer is a Diſcovery of the Falſity and Envy of this <hi>Looſe</hi> Charger.</p>
               <p>But as to what is here advanced, being what he ſays he <hi>Promiſed upon this Subject, in hopes that the</hi> Quakers, <hi>ſeeing the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prim. Her.</hi> P1..</note> 
                  <hi>original of their Errors, may bethink themſelves and return from whence they have fallen.</hi> I do tell him, that whatſoever his Promiſe was his Performance is very bad; becauſe, what he aſſigns for Original Errors, are but his Coppied Faſiti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s upon us (having been Charged by our Enemies ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Years paſt) and therefore we are very far from returning to Communion with one, whoſe Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is with the Father of Lies. As to the Oral Traditive Faith, by which he would <hi>Confirm Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm,</hi> tho' ſaid to be learned within 150 Years af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Chriſt,</hi> it is, what will not do it, for the ſame Antiquity and pretended Authority may be brought for Miſtakes more noted; But beſides, Faith is the Gift of God, to whom we muſt look for it, and not to the Mouths of Men: Indeed if he can abſolutely determine the queſtion by the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, the Work is done, and then there is no need of any doubtful help; but if not, it will not avail, tho' he bring many <hi>Clouds of ſuch Witneſſes</hi> in the latter Ages; and the Reaſon is plain, becauſe Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is (what he calls his Rule) not to be tried by them, but they by it, and if found contradictory thereto, our Diſſent cannot be Criminal: And not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:44459:8"/> he calls this <hi>A Cavil we learned from Elder Diſſenters;</hi> we are not afraid to ſtand by it, and therefore pay little Reverence to thoſe, nor any thing not purely Apoſtolical.</p>
               <p>Here he ſays, <hi>The late Repreſentations of Quakeriſm, hath given it quite another Turn and Face than it ever had before;</hi> if he had added <note place="margin">Ibid. p. 2.</note> [that he knew of] it had ſhewn ſome Modeſty, but ſince he has ſhewn none, I will tell him, he is Dogmatically Falſe; for our Principles are now no other than what they were when we were firſt a People, for Truth changes not; and this, I hope, will appear beyond Contradiction, from the many Quotations, I ſhall have occaſion to bring in, out of many of our former and latter Books; ſo that the Ground of what <hi>he calls our Schiſm</hi> (and which I ſay is our juſt Diſſent) will conſequently appear as large as before.</p>
               <p>He ſays, <hi>He hopes our Converſion is nigh, or if al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready Converted, our full Reconciliation to the Church.</hi> He ſhould have told us what Church he meanes; for if he means into Communion with himſelf, that is Scandalous (to ſay, <hi>no worſe at preſent)</hi> if he means to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> I cannot think ſhe would ſend a Rebellious Son to call us: And here I will take opportunity to Confute a Lying Boaſt, I have heard; and which is favoured by what him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf hath ſaid above, <hi>viz.</hi> He hath brought over a great many from Us: I know not, nor cannot hear (and I have inquired) of one Silly <hi>Quaker,</hi> who is yet ſo Ignorant, as to go from our Allowed Meetings, to his Unallowed One: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, when this his pretended Service is urged, as an Argument for his Attonement and Reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I can aſſure them the Argument is Falſe; and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:44459:8"/> there is great Reaſon it ſhould, for God advances not Truth by <hi>Piè fraudes,</hi> much leſs <hi>Impié frau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He changes Stile; and now Fawns, calling <hi>W. Penn, The Valuable Mr.</hi> Penn. At the end of his Book he changes again, and would there Inſinuate, This his now Valuable Mr. <hi>Penn</hi> to be there very weak; of which in its place.</p>
               <p>I ſhall here a little interrupt the Thread of my Diſcourſe upon this Pamphlet of <hi>Primitive Hereſie,</hi> &amp;c. and beſtow a few Words relating to his Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet or Diſcourſe of, <hi>Who are Qualified to Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Baptiſm and the Lord's Supper, together with the Cauſe of Epiſcopacy.</hi> But I ſhall not take much no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of it, not knowing any of us that want his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation in the firſt, and as for the laſt, I ſhall leave it to that Community to whom more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly it is directed; only thus much by the way I ſhall firſt obſerve, that I take this Pamphleteer to be no proper Adminiſtrator (notwithſtanding his noiſe for the Church) hebeing a Schiſmatick and Diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to (what he owns) the <hi>Jus divinum</hi> of his Biſhop. And next, that the noiſe he makes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us for Schiſmaticks, and offers <note place="margin">A Diſcourſe ſhewing who they are that are now Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> p. 18. 33.</note> againſt us, <hi>That Idolatry does not <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>church,</hi> and that <hi>Great things ought to be borne rather than run into it.</hi> It will not be foreign to the preſent Caſe to give the Eighth <hi>Article</hi> of the Churches Apology before-mentioned, wherein are Reaſons for their Separating from Communion with <hi>Rome.</hi> I hope the pertinency of the Citation will attone for its length:</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:44459:9"/>
               <p>
                  <q> Nos verò cum proximis iſti viginti annis, tot millia noſtrorum fratrum inter ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitiſſimos cruciatus Teſtimonium <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Apol.</hi> p. 5. <hi>Ar.</hi> 8.</note> dixerint veritati, &amp; Principes, cum fraenare cuperent Evangelium, multa moliendo nihil egerint; &amp; totus ſum prope terrarum orbis ad aſpiciendam lucem oculos incipiat aperire; ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis jam dictam &amp; defenſam putamus eſſe noſtram cauſam: cum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> res ipſo proſe lo quatur, non mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis opus eſſe verbis. Nam ſi pontifices ipſi vellent, aut etiam ſi poſſent, rem ipſam ſecum, &amp; initia progreſſuſque Religionis noſtrae cogitare, quem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>admodum ſua penè omnia nullo impelente, ſine ulla humana ope ceciderint: noſtra verò invitis ab initio Imperatoribus, invitis tot regibus, invitis pontificibus, invitis prope omnibus, in crementa ceperint; &amp; paulatim in omnes terras propagata fuerint, at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> etiam in poſtremo in regnum jam aulas &amp; palatia pervenerint, vel haec ipſa ſatis illis mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na eſſe poſſent; Deum ipſum pronobis propugnare, &amp; ipſorum conatus de Coelo ridere, &amp; eam eſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vim veritatis, quam nec humanae virés nec infero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum portae poſſunt convellere. Non enim inſani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt hodie tot civitates liberae, tot Reges, tot Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipes, quia à ſede romana defecerunt, &amp; ſe potius ad Chriſti Evangelium adjunxerunt. </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But we, for theſe paſt Twenty Years, have had ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Thouſands of our Brethren given Teſtimony to the Truth in exquiſite Torments; and Princes, when they ſought to ſtop the Goſpel, tho' with much Labour, effect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed nothing; and now near all the Earth begin to open their Eyes to ſee the Truth, and we think our Cauſe enough ſpoken to and defended; for if the</hi> Romaniſts <hi>will, or are able, to conſider the thing with themſelves, and think upon the Beginning and Progreſs of our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:44459:9"/> how that theirs almoſt no one forcing, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any humane help is fallen, but ours, from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, againſt the Will of Emperors, againſt the Will of Kings, againſt the Will of Popes, and againſt the Will of almoſt all, hath received increaſe, and by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees hath been Propagated in all Lands; and after Kingdoms, it is now come into Courts and Pallaces,</hi> THESE THINGS ALONE <hi>may be to them a great Indication, that</hi> GOD HIMSELF HATH FAUGHT FOR US, <hi>and hath Laughed from Heaven at all their</hi> ENDEAVOURS, <hi>and ſuch is the force of Truth, that neither Humane Strength nor the Gates of Hell can pluck it up. Neither are ſo many free Cities, ſo many Kings, and ſo many Princes</hi> MAD, <hi>becauſe they have ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the Sea of</hi> Rome, <hi>and rather joyned themſelves to the Goſpel of Chriſt.</hi> Thus the <hi>Apology.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If I ſhould now throughly ſhew, in how many Inſtances the above Deſcription has been our Caſe, it would ſwell this to an undue Bulk; and I ſhould be obliged to remember things; which time, and a better aminiſtration, have laid to Sleep: Not but that any of middle Age, and tollerable Obſervation are capable of calling to mind a great many inſtances wherein the Paralel Suits; and here I am the rather willing to leave it, not judging it meet to Recri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate upon a whole Body, for the Faults of an Excluded Member; who, while he is crying out againſt Schiſm and Schiſmaticks, forgets his own Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration and Diſobedience from a Power which he pretends to own, of which poſſibly more anon. What I particularly now make my Buſineſs, and to which I return, is to conſider his Scurrilous Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet, Entituled, <hi>PRIMITIVE HERESIE REVIVED,</hi> &amp;c. by which he hath Charged us, the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:44459:10"/> People called <hi>Quakers,</hi> in Faith and Practice, with divers Errors, the chief of which are, that we deny the Incarnation of Chriſt, the Truth and Reality of his Death and Sufferings, the Reſurrection and Future Judgment, that we deny Marriage, and Preach up Fornication, contemn Magiſtracy and Government; which Charges, tho' of the greateſt and fouleſt kind, he will not, as himſelf ſays, <hi>take up the Readers time to prove;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Prim. Her. Rev. p. 2.</note> but refers him to his former Books, which have been already anſwered, and his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſes and Falſities therein laid at his Door. So that if I reſolved to take his Example: I need ſay no more, than that theſe his Charges are, near all of them, already anſwered by <hi>George Whitehead,</hi> in the <hi>Antidete</hi> aforeſaid, and refer the Reader thither, and this I might the rather do, becauſe, for Forty or more Years paſt, there have been frequent and repeated Accounts of our Belief, in ſome or other of theſe things, as they have happened to be made Charges upon us by our Adverſaries during that time: But I am contented for this once <hi>Actum Agere,</hi> and to bring into this, out of ſeveral of our Ancient <hi>Friends Books,</hi> ſome account under each of theſe heads, whereby the <hi>Reader</hi> may ſee, that our <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Practice</hi> herein, ſince we have been a People, hath been a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable and conſonant to the Holy Scripture; and do ſo continue to this day: And if upon inquiry, we are found agreeable to that; I ſhall not matter whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we be ſo or not, to the controverted Records of uncertain, and unſound Antiquity: Nor ſhall we need be at all affrighted, if we do find our ſelves to differ; from what is to be found under the ſpecious names of <hi>Ignatius, Policarp,</hi> &amp;c. tho' living within 150 Years after Chriſt, nor under the great names of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:44459:10"/> them called <hi>Fathers</hi> in the ſucceeding Ages; of which Subject many have written, &amp; may have perhaps evin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, that the great uncertainty of not being deceiv'd by them, and the little advantage if not ſo; will not nor cannot admit us to value them ſo, as to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined by them rather than by the Holy Scriptures, which in this Nation, is commonly called the RULE of <hi>Faith.</hi> And tho' this Man to divert his cares, his fears, and to ſupply his wants, may ſpend his time in Catalogues of <hi>Hereſies,</hi> and the Stale Tracts of uncertain Perſons, to enable him to club Quotati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and clap them upon the back of Charges taken from our profeſt Adverſaries, from whom in part, he receives his Bread; yet I doubt not, but to bring in ſuch a train of Evidence in theſe Queſtions wherein we are ſaid to be Heretical, as will ſufficiently evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to the Impartial Reader, that the Charge, as as well as the Man, is falſe; and that our belief in theſe Articles is Scriptural: The Method I purpoſe to take herein, is this, I ſhall ſet down in a methodical order, the ſeveral Teſtimonies under each diſtinct Head, according to the priority of time in which they were written, ſo that upon a ſhort view, the Reader may have recourſe to each.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:44459:11"/>
               <head>Some Teſtimonies to Chriſt Jeſus, as the Son of God, and come in the Fleſh. SECT. II.</head>
               <p>Page 2, 3, 4. <q rend="inline"> WE Profeſs and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs <note place="margin">Books Titles</note> Faith in God the Father, and in Jeſus <note place="margin">
                        <hi>A Confeſſion and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Faith in God,</hi> &amp;c. 1651. <hi>by</hi> Rich. Farnſworth.</note> Chriſt his Eternal Son, the True God, and in the Holy Spirit: And we do acknowledge the Holy Scriptures of the Old and New Teſtament to be the Words of God.—And there is none other Gods but One, and this is God the Father which we own, <note place="margin">Iſa. 44. 8. 1 Cor. 8. 4. John 10. 30, 31 Mark 12. 29, 30, 31, 32, 33, 34. 1 Cor. 8. 5, 6. Rom. 4. 25. Iſaiah 45. 6. Eph. 4. 4, 5, 30. John 4. 24. Phil. 1. 1, 29.</note> and Profeſs Faith in, and in Jeſus Chriſt his Eternal Son, who ſaid, <hi>I and my Father are One</hi> (upon which ſaying the <hi>Jews</hi> took up <hi>Stones</hi> to Stone him) yet notwithſtanding the ſame <hi>Chriſt</hi> that the <hi>Jews</hi> hated, we love, belive in, and own, who was delivered up to be Crucified for our Offences, and was raiſed again for our Juſtification, who is the True God: And him we Own and Profeſs Faith in, and in the Holy Spirit, God; together equal with the Father and the Son, One God over all Bleſſed for ever. And unto us (and all True Chriſtians) the Saints in Chriſt Jeſus. It is given in the Behalf of Chriſt, not only to Believe on him, but alſo to Suffer for his Name ſake. </q>
               </p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:44459:11"/>
               <p>P. 10, 11. VII. <q rend="inline"> In the next place, truly to know this Lord Jeſus <note place="margin">
                        <hi>The One Good Way of God.</hi> Printed 1661. Written by <hi>Rich Hodden.</hi>
                     </note> Chriſt come in the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> as the New and Living Way to the Father, the <hi>Immanuel</hi> (God with us) making the Attonement by the Blood of his Croſs, to have all things ſubject unto him, his Servants in him, and he in them; which is the great My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of Godlineſs, his from Ages and Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions until the fulneſs of time, and then Manifeſted in the Fleſh, Juſtified in the Spirit, Believed on in the World, and Received up into Glory; which none of the Wiſe Men of the World ever knew, or can know by all their Learned Skill of Earthly Wiſdom; nor any Man that Lives after the Fleſh, or ſatisfieth himſelf with Hearing, Reading, Telling or Talking of him, or concerning what he or his Apoſtles did, ſaid or ſuffered; as thoſe that vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly take his Name into their Mouths (on moſt occaſions of their Invented Ways) but know him not, neither by his Divine Nature nor Name, nor HOW GOD AND MAN BECAME ONE CHRIST JESUS, how that which may be known of God is manifeſt in Man, how he is <hi>The Wonderful Counſellor, the Mighty God, the Prince. of Peace: The Author and Finiſher of our Faith. How he ſaves his People from their Sins,</hi> is the Reconciler without Imputation of Sin: How he is Formed in his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and Cleanſeth them by his Blood from all Sin and Unrighteouſneſs; how they take up the Croſs and follow him, or what the Croſs is; how the Body becomes Dead becauſe of Sin, and the Spirit Alive for Righteouſneſs ſake: How they are Members of his Body, of his Fleſh, and of his Bones; how he is their <hi>Loader, and Captain of</hi>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:44459:12"/> 
                     <hi>Salvation,</hi> made perfect through Sufferings: How they are Baptized into his Death, and Saved by his Life: How the Union is perfected in all the Parts and Members of his Body the Church: What the Church is, or how his Body; or what it is to eat his Fleſh, and drink his Blood; without which (as himſelf ſaid) we have no Life in us: How every Knee ſhall bow to him, of things in Heaven, in Earth, and under the Earth; and confeſs that Jeſus Chriſt is Lord, to the Glory of God the Father: How he is that Bleſſed and Only Potentate, King of Kings, and Lord of Lords, the Head of all Thrones and Dominions, and every Name that is named. </q>
               </p>
               <p>P. 2, 13, 14. This is anſwered in part already, by what is ſaid to <note place="margin">
                     <hi>A Vindication of the Principles and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices of the People called Quakers, 1665 By</hi> Geo. Biſhop.</note> the former Queſtion, which in effect is this—<q rend="inline"> That that which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightens, which ſhews a Man his Heart, his Reins, and tryeth them, which reproves; which makes manifeſt, is Chriſt the Light; which <hi>Chriſt</hi> is the ſame that was born of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> which was made Fleſh, which ſitteth at the right Hand of God, which was Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, Dead, roſe again from the Dead; and aſcended far above the Heavens, that he might fill all things, who when he was in the days of his Fleſh with his Diſciples, ſaid, <hi>It is expedient for you that I go away; for</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">John 16. 7. 8, 9, 10, 11.</note> 
                     <hi>if I go not away the Comforter will not come unto you; but if I depart I will ſend him unto you; and when he is come, he will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove the World of Sin, of Righteouſneſs, and of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; of Sin, becauſe they believe not in me; of Righteouſneſs, becauſe I go to my Father; and of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:44459:12"/> becauſe the Prince of the World is Judged.</hi> So that which reproves the World of Sin, of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, and of Judgment, the Spirit of Truth, which proceedeth from the Father, which teſtifies of Chriſt, which guideth into all Truth, is the thing that now is to be look'd to; <hi>Chriſt in you,</hi> the Hope of Glory; the Myſtery hid from Ages and Generations, but now made manifeſt to his Saints; the Riches of the Glory of the Myſtery: Now the Lord is that Spirit—<hi>And when the Spirit of Truth is come, he will</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">John 16. 13. 2 Cor. 3. 17.</note> 
                     <hi>guide you into all Truth. </hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q> Chriſt and the Light which is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, are not Two, but One; yet are <note place="margin">Ibil. p. 15.</note> they not ſo One, as that where Chriſt is, there is the Body that Suffered at <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> that was Fleſh; that proceeded from the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> that died, was buried, roſe again, and aſcended, for in that he ſitteth at the right Hand of God. But where the Light is, there is <hi>Chriſt, which was in the Beginning with God; by whom all things were made that was made. In whom was Life, and the Life was the Light of Men,</hi> John 1. 2, 3, 4. </q>
               </p>
               <p>P. 11, 12. <q rend="inline"> It is objected againſt us, who are called Quakers, That <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Concerning the Sum or Subſtance,</hi> &amp;c. Iſaac Pennington.</note> we deny Chriſt (and look not to be Saved by him) as he was ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted without us, but look on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be Saved by a Chriſt in us. To which this is in my Heart, to anſwer to ſuch as ſingly deſire ſatisfaction therein. </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q> We do indeed expect to be Saved (yea, and not only ſo, but do already in our ſeveral meaſures witneſs Salvation) by the Revelation and Operation of the Life of Chriſt within us; yet not without
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:44459:13"/> relation to what he did without us. For all that he did in that Body of Fleſh, was of the Father, and had its Place and Service in the Will, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Counſel of the Father. But the Knowledge and Belief of that, ſince the days of the Apoſtles, hath been very much held in the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs, and in the Separation from the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Work of the Power and Life of Chriſt in the Heart; which as ſo held cannot Save any. But whoever feels the Light and Life of Chriſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed in him, and comes into Union with God there-through, he feels the Work of Regeneration, of Sanctification, of Juſtification, of Life and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption; and ſo comes to reap Benefit inwardly, and to partake of the Bleſſed Fruits of all that Chriſt did outwardly. Yea, he that is thus one with Chriſt in the Spirit, cannot exclude himſelf, nor is excluded by God, from the Advantage of any thing, nor every thing that Chriſt did in that Body of Fleſh. </q>
               </p>
               <p>P. 243. <q rend="inline"> The Doctrines and Principles of the People called <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Immediate Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>By</hi> Geo. Keith.</note> Quakers, as well as the People, do indeed more acknowledge the Man Chriſt Jeſus, than any of them all: Inaſmuch as we do believe and acknowledge that a meaſure of the ſame Life and Spirit of the Man Chriſt Jeſus, which dwelt in him in its Fullneſs, and had its Center in him which came in the Fleſh, and was born of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and is now glorified in Heaven, is communicated unto us, and extends it ſelf into our Hearts and Souls, and whole In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Man, ſo that the Man Jeſus, who <hi>Simeon</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced with his Arms according to the Fleſh, is, according to the Spirit, our Life and Glory, by
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:44459:13"/> whom we receive Light, Grace and Truth, and through whom we have acceſs unto God. </q>
               </p>
               <p>P. 358. <q rend="inline"> Yet notwithſtanding for your Satisfaction, we do now <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Journal.</hi> Geo. Fox.</note> plainly and ſincerely declare, That we <hi>Own</hi> and <hi>Believe in God,</hi> the Only Wiſe Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent and Everlaſting God, who is the <hi>Creator</hi> of all things both in Heaven and in the Earth, and the <hi>Preſerver</hi> of all that he hath made; who is <hi>God</hi> over all Bleſſed for ever: To whom be all Honour and Glory, Dominion, Praiſe and Thankſgiving, both now and for evermore. And we do <hi>Own</hi> and <hi>Believe in Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> his beloved and only begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Son, in whom he is well pleaſed; who was Conceived by the Holy Ghoſt, and Born of the Virgin <hi>Mary;</hi> in whom we have <hi>Redemption</hi> through his <hi>Blood,</hi> even the <hi>Forgiveneſs</hi> of <hi>Sins:</hi> Who is the <hi>expreſs Image of the Inviſible God,</hi> the Firſt-born of every Creature, by whom were all things created that are in Heaven, and that are in Earth, Viſible and Inviſible, whether they be Thrones, or Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, or Principalities, or Powers; all things were Created by him. And we do <hi>Own</hi> and <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve</hi> that He was made a Sacrifice for Sin; who knew no <hi>Sin,</hi> neither was <hi>Guile</hi> found in his Mouth. And that he was <hi>Crucified</hi> for us in the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Gates of <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> and that he was <hi>Buried,</hi> and <hi>Roſe</hi> again the <hi>Third</hi> day, by the <hi>Power</hi> of his <hi>Father,</hi> for our <hi>Juſtification:</hi> And we do <hi>Believe</hi> that he <hi>aſcended</hi> up into <hi>Heaven,</hi> and now ſitteth at the <hi>right Hand of God.</hi> This <hi>Jeſus,</hi> who was the <hi>Foundation</hi> of the <hi>Holy Prophets</hi> and <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> is our Foundation: And we do Believe that there is no other <hi>Foundation</hi> to be laid, but that which is laid, even <hi>Chriſt Jeſus;</hi> who we <hi>Believe</hi> taſted
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:44459:14"/> 
                     <hi>Death</hi> for <hi>every Man,</hi> and ſhed his <hi>Blood</hi> for <hi>all Men,</hi> and is the <hi>Propitiation</hi> for our <hi>Sins,</hi> and not for ours only, but alſo for the <hi>Sins</hi> of the <hi>whole World. </hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>P. 149. <q rend="inline"> We do Believe in One Only Holy God Almighty, who <note place="margin">
                        <hi>A Serious Apology,</hi> &amp;c. 1671. <hi>By</hi> G. Whitehead <hi>and</hi> W. Penn.</note> is an Eternal Spirit, the Creator of all things. And in <hi>One Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> his Only Son, and <hi>expreſs Image of his Subſtance,</hi> who took upon him Fleſh, and was in the World, and in Life, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, Miracles, Death, Reſurrection, Aſcention and Mediation, perfectly did and does continue to do the Will of God; to whoſe <hi>Holy Life, Power, Mediation and Blood, we only aſcribe our Sanctification, Juſtification, Redemption, and Perfect Salvation.</hi> And we Believe in <hi>One Holy Spirit,</hi> that proceeds and breaths from the Father and the Son, as the Life and Vertue of both the Father and the Son, <hi>a mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of which is given to all to profit with;</hi> and he that has one has all, for thoſe <hi>Three are One,</hi> who is <hi>the Alpha and Omega, the Firſt and the Laſt,</hi> God over all Bleſſed for ever, <hi>Amen. </hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>To theſe foregoing Citations I could add very many more, both of older and later date, but as I would not needleſly quote Inſtances, ſo I hope the Reader will not account me hitherto Superfluous, in reſcuing our ſelves from Calumny and Abuſe, in a Charge which appears ſo plainly to be Falſe; for a plain as is the Sun when on its Meridian, ſo plain is it that we ſincerely own, and heartily believe, all that the Holy Scriptures teſtifie concerning the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and the Union of both Natures, that is, as God and Man.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:44459:14"/>
               <head>SECT. III.</head>
               <p>HIS next Calumny in the order of his Charge is, That we deny the Truth and Reality of his Death and Sufferings. In proof of our Belief whereof, I am already in good part prevented, by the foregoing Teſtimonies; in almoſt all of which, there is ſome mention of his Crucifixion, as well as of his Birth: But however I am content to anſwer <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>abundanti,</hi> not wanting Inſtances of our Belief here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, from whence I can allow Meaſure preſſed down and running over.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Some Teſtimonies to the Truth and Reality of <hi>Chriſt's</hi> Death and Suffering.</head>
                  <p>Page 3. <q rend="inline"> Before <hi>Abraham</hi> was, I am; who was in the Beginning, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>The Path of the Juſt Cleared, 1655. By</hi> G. Whitehead.</note> which was the Word, by which all things were made, which Word became Fleſh, and dwelt among <note place="margin">John 8. 58. John 1.</note> the Diſciples, and Suffered at <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> and witneſſed a good Confeſſion before <hi>Pontius Pilate,</hi> whom <hi>Pilate</hi> delivered up to the Jews, and the Chief Prieſts and Elders, whom they <hi>mocked and deſpitefully uſed,</hi> and put to Death con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Fleſh; but is raiſed up by the Spirit, and aſcended into Glory, which Glory he prayed for, even that Glory <note place="margin">John 17. John 5. 22. John 10. 30.</note> whereby he was at firſt by his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther glorified in, wherein he is glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified in his Saints, and is God over all Bleſſed for ever. </q>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:44459:15"/>
                  <p>Page 4. <q rend="inline">
                        <hi> Chriſt,</hi> in dying for us, is our Example in Sufferings, and <note place="margin">
                           <hi>The Brazen Serpent lifted up,</hi> &amp;c. 1655. <hi>By</hi> R. Farnſworth.</note> way to the Father, for Chriſt in Dying for Sinners and Ungodly, died for all; for was not all Sinners and Ungodly guilty of <hi>Chriſt's</hi> Death; but it is by his Blood that we are Juſtified, and by his Life that we are Saved—In following his Counſel and obeying him, through the Croſs which ſlays the Enmity, as he became obedient to the Death of the Croſs, who is our Leader and Example, and is the Author of Eternal Salvation to all that obey him, but none elſe. </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <q> We believe that all things which are ſpoken by the Holy <note place="margin">
                           <hi>A new Catechiſm, 1664. By</hi> W. Smith.</note> Prophets and Apoſtles concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſt, are true according to the Scriptures: We believe that all the Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations of God, which are manifeſted by the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, are altogether true, and that they were all fulfilled according to the determinate Will and Counſel of God: So that our Faith concerning <hi>Chriſt</hi> in us, and the Work which he there worketh for us, doth not all make void any of the Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations of God, which in times paſt were revealed unto his Holy Prophets and Apoſtles, and by them teſtified in the Scriptures; ſo that the Work which the Father then gave unto the Son to do, we believe that he fulfilled according to the Father's Will, and that all things pertaining to Life and Salvation were FULLY and PERFECTLY in him, and that he humbled himſelf to the Death of the Croſs, and from Death did riſe again: And we believe that he is the Reſurrection and the Life, and gives Eternal Life to all that believe in him. </q>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:44459:15"/>
                  <p>P. 19, 20. <q rend="inline"> We Believe and Teſtifie, that this <hi>Jeſus</hi> of <hi>Nazaretio</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rebellion Rebuked,</hi> &amp;c. 167. <hi>by</hi> John Crook <hi>and</hi> William Bayly.</note> wrought out, fulfilled all Righteouſneſs in his Obedience, both in DOING and SUFFER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ING the Holy Law and Will of God, and that this Righteouſneſs ſo wrought out and fulfilled, was not for himſelf, but for, or becauſe of all ſuch as truly, ſeeing they have no Covering or Righteouſneſs of their own, flee unto, and lay hold of him and his Everlaſting Righteouſneſs, by a True and Living Faith.—We Believe and Teſtifie, That his Blood exceeds not only the Blood of Bulls and of Goats, but the Blood of the beſt Man or Men that ever was, or ſhall be, in the World. And we do, in the ſight of God, really own the Blood of the Son of Man; both according to the Hiſtory, and in the Myſtery (as we do his Croſs) both as Shed for us, and to be Drank by us; both as beſpeaking Remiſſion of Sin paſt through Faith in it; and as Sprinkling the Conſcience of True Believers, and Cleanſing them from all Sin.—But becauſe we Teſtifie, that it's not the Notion, or bare Hiſtorical and Literal Belief of thoſe things, that Juſtifie, or make us Really free from that which comes upon every Soul of Man that doth Evil, whether <hi>Jew</hi> or <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile, Profeſſor</hi> or <hi>Prophane,</hi> but only the Life and Virtue of this Blood received into the Heart, by that Living Faith, which Chriſt alone is the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of. Therefore are we Branded with Slight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Blood of the Man <hi>Chriſt,</hi> &amp;c. though we Teſtifie our Eſteem thereof, both in the Hiſtory and in the Myſtery, and that without the Life and Virtue of this Blood there is no Remiſſion. </q>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:44459:16"/>
                  <p>P. 9.—<q rend="inline"> Therefore we do Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs to his Sufferings, according <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Truths Vindication,</hi> &amp;c. 1679. Eliz. Bathurſt.</note> to the Scriptures; for Chriſt alſo hath once Suffered for Sin, the Juſt for the Unjuſt, that he might bring us to God; being put to <hi>Death in the Fleſh, but Quickened in the Spirit;</hi> we <note place="margin">1 Peter 3. 18.</note> own his Death, as an Acceptable and moſt Satisfactory Sacrifice to God for the Sins of all, and is of Bleſſed Advantage to all that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Faith in his Blood, <hi>Whom God hath ſet forth to be a Propitiation through</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Rom. 3. 25. Eph. 5. 2.</note> 
                        <hi>his Blood to declare his Righteouſneſs for the Remiſſion of Sins that are paſt, through the Forbearance of God; and he hath given himſelf for us an Offering and a Sacrifice to God for a Sweet Smelling Savour.</hi> Alſo we Believe, that as Chriſt Died for our Sins, ſo he was Buried like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, and roſe again according to the Scriptures. <hi>But now is Chriſt</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15. 3, 4. 20. 21.</note> 
                        <hi>Riſen from the Dead, and become the firſt Fruits of them that Sleep: For ſince by Man came Death, by Man came alſo the Reſurrection of the Dead.</hi> The Apoſtle mentions this as the Aſſurance which God gave to Men, of his Judging the World at the Great Day, by his <hi>Son Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <note place="margin">Acts 17. 31.</note> his having Raiſed him from the Dead. </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>P. 31, 32. <q rend="inline"> And the Preaching of this <hi>Jeſus,</hi> Powerful Shepherd and <note place="margin">
                           <hi>A Mirrour,</hi> &amp;c. 1683. <hi>by</hi> Sam. Wattſon.</note> Biſhop of our Souls, was in the Heavenly Authority of his Father in which he ſpoke forth all things appertaining to Life and Salvation, and are left upon Record by
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:44459:16"/> thoſe who were Witneſſes of his Coming in a moſt Special Manner, by <hi>Matthew, Mark, Luke,</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> who were Witneſſes, with many more, of his Doctrine, Life and Suffering, which laid <hi>down his Life for his Sheep;</hi> as 'tis Written, <hi>They ſtripped him, and put on him a Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Mat. 27. 28.</note> 
                        <hi>Robe, and when they had platted a Crown of Thorns, they put it on his Head, Nailing him to the Croſs, Spitting upon him, and Mocking him, ſaying, Hail</hi> KING <hi>of the</hi> Jews; tho' he had done nothing worthy of Death; yet the Hard-hearted, who Rejected the Corner Stone, ſaid, <hi>We have a Law, and by our Law this Man muſt Die.</hi> So, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing the Juſt One, and the Saviour of the World, they choſe <hi>Barrabas</hi> to Live. This Cruelty Acted it ſelf in a Guileful Spirit, to Deſtroy him in whom was found no Guile, neither ever was it in his Mouth. This is he who Suffered under <hi>Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius Pilate;</hi> was Crucified, Dead and Buried, and the Third Day Roſe again; who aſcended, and ſitteth at the Right Hand of God the Father, from whence by his own Power he comes to Judge both the Quick and the Dead. This is he in whom I Believe, and is my Saviour, in and through whoſe Precious Blood is my Salvation and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, and not in another (which Thouſands with me are Witneſſes of) whoſe Bleſſed Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe we Believe in, and in meaſure made parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of, that he would <hi>ſend the Comforter, the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Truth,</hi> whom the World could not receive, becauſe they knew him not; he ſhall bring all things to Remembrance, and ſhall lead and guide into all Truth; <hi>And he that is in you, ſhall be with you to the end of the World.</hi> This is the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Saviour, whoſe Appearance is in Spirit, as the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:44459:17"/> Apoſtle Teſtifies of his Second Appearance with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Sin to Salvation, which cannot be known but by his Spiritual Work in the Inner Man, whoſe Appearance and Manifeſtation is to Deſtroy the Works of the Devil, which is Sin, Unbelief, and all Unrighteouſneſs whatſoever, that he alone may Rule and Reign in Man and Woman, who brings Salvation to their Houſe. </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>This his Second Charge, of our Denial of the Truth and Reality of Chriſt's Death and Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings is, I think, by the foregoing Teſtimonies, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently Cleared; it appearing from them, that his Charge, of our having <hi>left the Body of Chriſt, as a Forſaken Vail and Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Prim. Here.</hi> &amp;c. P. 7.</note> 
                     <hi>to Rot in the Grave. And Care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs of what is become of it, as a thing now of no Virtue or Conſequence with <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s,</hi> is Falſe, if a Succeſſion of Teſtimonies of our Belief herein, produced for about Forty Years can Prove it; yet if theſe are Judged too few, I have many more in Store; not that I can at all doubt that theſe are not enough to ſatisfie Honeſt Enquirers at a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance; and alſo to Invite them to a nearer View of us herein, and in the whole Syſtem of one Faith, it being for the ſake of ſuch, that we find our ſelves Concerned, to Oppoſe the Truth of our Profeſſion, to the Falſity of our Enemies Charges. For with reſpect to our ſelves, we do Enjoy great Peace and Quiet, though thus Evilly ſpoken of, as knowing, it was by our <hi>Saviour</hi> ſo foretold it ſhould be, who alſo himſelf was ſaid to have a Devil, to be a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducer, a Samaritan, and a Winebiber, his Apoſtles and Servants of Old, found ſuch-like Treatment, <hi>Stephen</hi> being Stoned, as a Contemner of God, of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:44459:17"/> his Law, of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and of the Temple: And the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> was accounted a Heretick, a Deceiver, a Mad-man, a Blaſphemer, a Seditious Perſon, and a Contemner of the Law of his Fathers. What better may we then expect from the ſame Spirit working in that Snake, which hides himſelf in Graſs or other Subterfuge.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>SECT. IV.</head>
               <p>I Come now to his third Charge, <hi>That we deny the Reſurrection, and Future Judgment,</hi> which upon enquiry, will be found as Falſe as the foregoing Charges, and it cannot well be otherwiſe, for it is next to impoſſible to be Orthodox in them, and Heretical in this, their dependance on each other is ſuch: And the Apoſtle's Argument is very ſtrong; <hi>If we had hope only in this Life, we were of all Men moſt Miſerable:</hi> For true Religion cannot incline a Man to believe and be obedient to ſuch Principles, as here expoſe him to utmoſt Dangers, and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after to no Joys: Chriſtianity is a Complex of more rational Truths, than ſo to Claſh and Jarr: And however Fooliſh the Man accounts us, we are more Learned in the School of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> than to deny or be ignorant of ſo ineſtimable an Advantage, as is the Reſurrection by <hi>Chriſt</hi> to Eternal Glory, and of that Future Judgment by which the States of Men muſt be determined. I now ſubjoyn ſome Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies hereof.</p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:44459:18"/>
               <p>P. 4, 5 of his Works. <q rend="inline"> Therefore Wo be unto all Epicures, who <note place="margin">
                        <hi>The Lying Spirit,</hi> &amp;c. 1658. William Smith.</note> put the Judgment of the Lord afar off, and ſit down at eaſe in the Fleſh, and make their Belly their God, mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Earthly things, devouring God's Creation to ſatisfie a Luſtful Appetite, and ſo Treaſuring up Wrath againſt the Day of Wrath, and Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Righteous Judgment of God, who will render to every Man according to his Deeds, when the Workers of Iniquity will not be known by him, but muſt all depart from him into Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Fire, there to abide under the Eternal Judgment. </q>
               </p>
               <p>P. 332. <q rend="inline"> And he that dieth in his Sins, not believing in the <note place="margin">Humphry Smith's <hi>Works, about</hi> 1660.</note> Light, which makes an end of Sin, cannot come where <hi>Chriſt</hi> is, and ſo the Tree falling there it lieth; and as Death leaveth, Judgment findeth; ſo ſhall the Reward according to the Deeds be; and then ſhall every Man ſtand or fall to his own Maſter; the Servants of the Devil to their Maſter, and the Servants of God to their Maſter; and there is no more Maſters but them two, and no Man can ſerve them both. </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q> Again concerning <hi>Chriſt,</hi> We believe that he is one with the <note place="margin">Edward Burroughs <hi>his Works,</hi> P. 440.</note> Father, and was with him before the World was; and what the Father worketh, it is by the Son; for he is the Arm of God's <hi>Salvation,</hi> and the very Power and Wiſdom of the Creator; and was, is, and is to come, without Beginning or End. </q>
               </p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:44459:18"/>
               <p>
                  <q> And we believe, That all the Prophets gave Teſtimony to him, and that he was made Manifeſt in <hi>Judea</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and did the Work of the Father, and was Proſecuted of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and was Crucified by his Enemies; and that he was Buried, and roſe again according to the Scriptures. </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q> And we believe, he is now aſcended on High, and exalted at the right Hand of the Father for evermore; and that he is glorified with the ſame Glory that he had before the World was; and that even the ſame that came down from Heaven, is aſcended up to Heaven; and the ſame that deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended is he that aſcended. </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q> And we believe, even that he that was Dead is Alive, and lives for evermore; and that he cometh, and ſhall come again, to Judge the whole World with Righteouſneſs, and all People with Equity, and ſhall give every Man according to his Deeds at the Day of Judgment, when all ſhall riſe to <hi>Condemnation</hi> or <hi>Juſtification;</hi> he that hath done good, ſhall receive Life, and he that hath done Evil, Everlaſting Condemnation. </q>
               </p>
               <p>P. 197. of his Works. <q rend="inline"> And thus in the Blindneſs of their Uncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed <note place="margin">
                        <hi>God's Virtue,</hi> &amp;c. 1670. <hi>By</hi> Tho. Taylor.</note> Hearts, they heap up Wrath againſt the Day of Wrath, and Revelation of God's Juſt Judgments upon them. Where is he that comes from the Dead, to tell us what is in another World; Let's Eat and Drink, and take our Fill of Pleaſures, for to morrow we Dye and are not, ſay they. </q>
               </p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:44459:19"/>
               <p>P. 9. <q rend="inline">
                     <hi> And how God hath anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Jeſus of</hi> Nazareth <hi>with the</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>A Teſtimony,</hi> &amp;c. 1677. <hi>By</hi> George Fox.</note> 
                     <hi>Holy Ghoſt, and with Power, who went about doing good, and Healing all that were Oppreſſed of the Devil, for God was with him; and we are Witneſſes of all things which he did, both in the Land of the Jews, and in</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>whom they ſlew and hanged on a Tree, him God raiſed up the third day, and ſhewed him openly, and we did eat and drink with him after he aroſe from the Dead, and he commanded us</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Acts 10. 41.</note> 
                     <hi>to preach unto the People, and to teſtifie that it is he that is ordained of God, a Judge of Quick and Dead.</hi> And to this do we teſtifie, which are the People of God in Scorn called Quakers. </q>
               </p>
               <p>P. 159. of his Works. <q rend="inline"> Marvel not at this, for the Hour is <note place="margin">
                        <hi>A Catechiſm, 1673. By</hi> Robert Barclay.</note> coming, in which all that are in the Graves ſhall hear his Voice, and ſhall come forth; they that have done good, to the Reſurrection of Life; and they that have done evil, to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection <note place="margin">John 3. 28, 29.</note> of Condemnation. <hi>But the Heavens and the Earth which are</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">2 Peter 3. 7.</note> 
                     <hi>now, by the ſame word are kept in ſtore, reſerved unto Fire againſt the Day of Judgment, and Perdition of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodly Men. </hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q> The Angels which fell had a State of Reſt and Peace with <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Election and Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation,</hi> p. 24. 1678. <hi>By</hi> William Gibſon.</note> God; this was the firſt State which <hi>Jude</hi> here ſpeaks of, but they kept not this firſt State and Habitation, but left it, yea, loſt it, through Preſumption, Irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:44459:19"/> and Neglect of their Duty, whom God in his Righteous Judgments hath reſerved in Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Chains under Darkneſs, unto the Judgment of the Great Day. </q>
               </p>
               <p>P. 3. <q rend="inline"> For at the Great Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunal Chriſt Jeſus will not fear <note place="margin">
                        <hi>An Antichriſtian Conſpiracy,</hi> &amp;c. 1679. <hi>By</hi> Tho. Wynne.</note> to tell them, it was Work of Iniquity; For, ſaid he, <hi>Inaſmuch as ye have done it to one of the leaſt of my Brethren, ye have done it unto me. </hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>P. 7. <q rend="inline"> The <hi>Quakers</hi> deny no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection that is according to <note place="margin">
                        <hi>A Brief Anſwer,</hi> &amp;c. 1678. <hi>By</hi> W. P.</note> Scripture; we own the Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction both of the Juſt and Unjuſt; we declare to all People, we own the Reſurrection of the Body, according to the Pleaſure of God: And every Seed ſhall have its own Body; and Wo to the Wicked in that Day. </q>
               </p>
               <p>P. 13. <q rend="inline"> And if Chriſt did ſay to them that in his Members did not <note place="margin">
                        <hi>The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nequal <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yoaked,</hi> &amp;c. 1683. <hi>By</hi> Peter Price.</note> viſit him in Priſon, <hi>Depart from me, ye Curſed, into Everlaſting Fire, prepared for the Devil and his Angels;</hi> What will he ſay to you, that do caſt him in his Members into Priſon? Seeing Chriſt ſaid ſo to them that were too ſhort in their Duty towards his People, What will he ſay to you, <note place="margin">Matt. 25. 32.</note> that are Cruel and Spiteful towards his People? Read theſe Scriptures to the end, and you may ſee the Reward both of the Godly and Ungodly, the Portion of the Faithful and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithful. </q>
               </p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:44459:20"/>
               <p>
                  <q> This is not to Rule for God, an Account you muſt give, to <note place="margin">William Deusberry p. 394. <hi>of his Works.</hi>
                     </note> the Judge of Heaven and Earth. Oh Men! How will you ſtand in that Day, when it ſhall be ſaid unto you, <hi>I was Sick and in Priſon, and you Viſited me not; Hungry, and you gave me no Meat; Naked, and you Cloathed me not; a Stranger, and you took me not in.</hi> The Day is near, to this Account you will be called by the Lord of Life and Glory. </q>
               </p>
               <p>P. 204. <q rend="inline"> We own the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, and do believe that the <note place="margin">John Burnyat <hi>in his Works.</hi>
                     </note> Righteous ſhall aſcend into Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and be Glorified in Heaven with an Eternal Reward; and that the Wicked alſo ſhall Riſe and come to Judgment, and be turned into Hell, to receive an Eternal Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. </q>
               </p>
               <p>Here I have brought Twelve Witneſſes, to Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie contrary to this Man's Falſe Charge; which they do ſo Scripturally, and Truly, as Effectually to wipe it off, and leave no room for this Snake of Envy to hide himſelf in a Colour of Truth; if it may be allowed more reaſonable for a Man to Declare his own Faith, than to be obliged to ſtand by the Declaration of it made by his Enemy. And this Man, is Wilfully or Ignorantly, unknowing of our Belief herein: For we continue to ſay, That in order to Salvation, Man muſt in this Life Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs the Redeeming Power of <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> to Quicken and Raiſe him out of Sin, which, when Man does Witneſs, he is then in Scripture Acception, <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker of him who is the Firſt Reſurrection.</hi> And every
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:44459:20"/> Man ſo Redeemed, and Raiſed, does Faithfully, and of neceſſity muſt, Believe the Future Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection into Eternal Glory; and the Future Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the Wicked to Everlaſting Torments. As for the Body, 1 <hi>Cor. 15. 37. Thou ſoweſt not that Body that ſhall be.</hi> But we are Heartily Satisfied with the Apoſtle, Verſe 38. <hi>That God giveth it a Body as it pleaſeth him.</hi> Our Belief herein hath often been Declared, notwithſtanding which, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we are not Fooliſhly Querying, as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſays ſome were, <hi>with what Bodies the Dead are Raiſed,</hi> they will needs have us <hi>Hereticks:</hi> The Groſs Conception, concerning Reſurrection of Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, is well Contradicted by a Biſhop in a late Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon before the King, <hi>viz.</hi> 
                  <q rend="inline"> We ſhall at laſt eſcape out of this Vile World, and from theſe Vile Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies: We ſhall ariſe above the Depreſſion of Senſe and Imagination, and the Diſorders of Appetite and Paſſion. We ſhall drop our Bodies, with all the Neceſſities and Weakneſſes that hang about them, and ſhall ariſe into a State of Pure and Clear Light; into a State of Purity and Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; into the Angels and Saints, and be brought to ſee and enjoy God to all Eternity; and that too with all the Fulneſs of Comprehenſion, as well as Joy, that our Faculties in their utmoſt En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largment and Elevation are Capable of.</q> Of this enough is ſaid here; I muſt now look upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Line of this our Adverſaries, and I have found a very ill one in p. 9. That we think our <hi>own Fleſh and Blood, to be the Fleſh and Blood of Chriſt,</hi> &amp;c. But it happens that I have brought ſome among the foregoing Teſtimonies againſt it, and he only Urges himſelf for an Authority, who I ſhall anon prove to be a Splitter of Sentences, an Enemy to Colons
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:44459:21"/> and Semicolons, and Orthodox Doctrines, when in a <hi>Quakers</hi> Book.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>SECT. V.</head>
               <p>HIS Fourth Charge is, That we <hi>Abſtain from the Sacraments, and the Prayers of the Church;</hi> which he ſeems to think of ſuch Moment, as to be the <hi>Guards of the Truth, and Importance of Chriſt's Outward Sufferings,</hi> and that where taken away, <hi>Men fall from the True Faith in them.</hi> But then <hi>è contrae</hi> it ſhould follow, that where theſe are, there True Faith remains, which does not appear either in his own, nor the Practice of very many others who have them: But if Fellowſhip in Miſery is any ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage; enough of Company he has afforded us, for there is a pretty many up and down in the World that do not uſe his Prayers. As for our ſelves, I muſt truly Confeſs, <hi>That we know not how to Pray as we ought, but the Spirit it ſelf helpeth our Infirmities.</hi> And I take the Holy Spirit to be a Surer Guide, both for Time, Matter and Manner of Prayer, than what he would give us in the ſtead thereof. But here he is ſo ſure of his Charge, that he makes Quotations; his firſt is out of, <hi>News out of the</hi> North, by <hi>G. Fox;</hi> I cannot Examine it, not having the Book by me; but I much queſtion the Truth of the Quotation, as anon it may be the Reader will think I have cauſe. His next Quotation is out of <hi>Edward Borrough's,</hi> p. 190. of his <hi>Works;</hi> it was well for me that I had this direction, or elſe I know not how I ſhould have found it; for as the Words lye in his Charge, they are not like
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:44459:21"/> 
                  <hi>E. B's</hi> Words: The Snake has here declared him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf an Enemy to well-plac'd Stops, and given us to underſtand, that he more Merits Advancement in <hi>Spain</hi> than in <hi>England:</hi> He begins a Quotation thus, <hi>Their Doctrines are of the Devil, who—</hi>(but he has left out what follows) <hi>denies the Truth which the Scripture bears Witneſs of.</hi> Thus good things are ſpoiled by ill Handling, and Orthodox Sentences made Heretical; but this is not to be wondered at, when an Inquiſitor has Cut, or a Snake Bit them. His next Quotation is in p. 191. and here he is playing the like Pranks; for when he has made up a Period, pick'd out of three places, the laſt of them Concludes, <hi>Theſe are Damnable He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies, even to the Denying the Lord that bought them;</hi> (And leaving out what follows, and which ſhews who they are that do ſo) <hi>for they Deny the Light of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt given to every Man, to be the only Teacher, and the only Guide of Man; and they that do deny the Light of Chriſt, with which every Man that comes into the World is Lighted, to be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to lead to Chriſt, and to the Kingdom of God (as theſe Teachers in this Age do) they do deny the Lord that bought them.</hi> He continues his Quotation out of Page 644. of <hi>E. B's</hi> Works, but here, as before, he hath cut off, <hi>I ſhould ſhew you according to Scripture.</hi> Sure this Man has an Enmity to the Holy Scriptures, when mentioned by us, that he thus cuts out the Word when he meets it in his way. But by this time it may appear, that his Charge of Hideous Blaſphemy and Outrage, proves to be, a Hideous Stinking Vapour; and that himſelf de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves to be added to the Congregation, at the next Edition of the <hi>Index Expurgatorii.</hi> Page 10. Speaking of his <hi>Diſcourſe of Water-Baptiſm,</hi> he ſays,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:44459:22"/> 
                  <hi>It ſeems to have had ſome Effects already, even with</hi> G. Whitehead <hi>himſelf.</hi> He ſays true; it has had ſome Effect, for it did occaſion a Chapter in <hi>G. Whitehead's</hi> Anſwer, <hi>An Antidote,</hi> &amp;c. in which Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the Malice and Impertinency of that Diſcourſe is ſome-what ſhewn. But if he thinks it had any other Effect, the Boaſt is full as Vain and Falſe as his former ones; of which I have already taken notice. This will beſt appear by <hi>G. Whitehead's</hi> own Words, which he has neither fully nor truly given, by ſo imperfectly Quoting them: The place in Page 114. of the <hi>Antidote</hi> is this, <q rend="inline"> Yet others being more Conſcientiouſly tender in the Obſervation thereof, we are the more tender to theſe, ſo as not to Cenſure or Condemn them, meerly for Practicing that which they believe is their duty, either in Break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Bread, or Water-Baptiſm; yet deſire they may ſee further, and come under the Higher and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelical Diſpenſation of the Spiritual Communion and Bread of Life, and Cup of Bleſſing from Heaven (which can only Nouriſh the Soul unto Eternal Life) and of the Spiritual Baptiſm of Chriſt, which only is the Souls Sanctifying and Saving Baptiſm; ſo that this One Baptiſm, and this One Bread, which is the Subſtance they may Livingly partake of.</q> Now <hi>Charles,</hi> from thy Maiming of this place, it is much eaſier for <hi>George Whitehead,</hi> and all that will Read it, to be confirmed in a Certain Knowledge of thy Baſeneſs, than to be Converted to the Communion of One, who makes Lies his Refuge, and Deceit his Support.</p>
               <p>As to our Belief, with Reſpect to Baptiſm and the Supper, it has been very frequently Publiſhed, in Oppoſition to the Falſe Conſtructions of our Enemies, and while we moſt Stedfaſtly Believe,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:44459:22"/> Aſſert, and in meaſure Witneſs; that Baptiſm, which is not <hi>a putting away the Filth of the Fleſh:</hi> And that Holy Supper, of which Chriſt hath ſaid, <hi>I will come into him, and Sup with</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 3. 20.</note> 
                  <hi>him, and he with me;</hi> we cannot go back to leſs Beneficial Types. Who pleaſe to ſee theſe, Scripturally and very Largely Defended and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſed, may find it done in <hi>Robert Barclay's</hi> Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, which is very eaſie to be had, whether I refer the Honeſt Reading Enquirers for further ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction herein: And come to his next Charge of being <hi>Gnoſticks, Denying Marriage, and Preaching up Fornication.</hi> He might have as eaſily ſaid, We were <hi>Nicolatians;</hi> and then, upon an expreſs Text, War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted our Damnation. It is time for us to examine his <hi>Charge;</hi> why that is, That the <hi>People</hi> called <hi>Quakers</hi> forbid to Marry, and Preach up Fornication; which is implied in the Title Page, and abundantly Charged in the Contents. This is general enough; for I cannot find one Married or Single <hi>Quaker</hi> left out. Now it is time to Prove it, when it is ſo home laid: in order for Proof, I come to Page 12. and there he ſays, He does not <hi>Charge all the</hi> Quakers <hi>with this; no, nor the greateſt Number of them; only thoſe called New</hi> Quakers <hi>in America.</hi> The firſt Charge runs over <hi>England,</hi> and all the reſt of the World, where there are <hi>Quakers;</hi> the laſt is Limited only to <hi>America. Ah</hi> Charles! <hi>Doſt think this Looſneſs will carry thee off:</hi> This is a very Looſe way of Charging, and is at beſt an Equivocal Lie: But after <hi>his haſty running from his Charge,</hi> he ſtops at a diſtance; <hi>But the</hi> Quakers <hi>are thus far Anſwerable, That all this Wild Extravagance is a Natural Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of their Common Principle, and Notion of the Light within.</hi> I looked for his Proofs, but he has
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:44459:23"/> none here, and therefore I ſuppoſe it is, he asks us two Queſtions, to ſee if he can Snap us with Poor Silly Anſwers. (For it is a Jeſt to think he will allow us any other.) Well, ſince I can get no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe from him, I will take his Queſtions; which are:</p>
               <p>
                  <q> Now let me ask the Old <hi>Quakers,</hi> Are they the <hi>Children of the Reſurrection?</hi> They muſt anſwer, <hi>Yea,</hi> or go againſt their own Avowed Principles: And if <hi>Yea,</hi> then the Text is plain againſt their Marrying. </q>
               </p>
               <p>This is a Shrewd Queſtion, and has a Strange Conſequence; but I ſhall not Reply to it till I have given the other Queſtion too.</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="inline">
                     <hi> Let me ask again, Are they</hi> THE CHILDREN OF THIS WORLD? <hi>They will all ſay,</hi> NAY, <hi>For that is the common Epithet by which they De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe the</hi> WICKED; <hi>and is a Term that they put in Oppoſition to</hi> THE CHILDREN OF THE LIGHT, <hi>which they beſtow upon</hi> THEMSELVES. <hi>Now it is Written, That</hi> THE CHILDREN OF THIS WORLD MARRY. <hi>Therefore ſay the New</hi> Quakers, MARRYIAGE IS A WICKED THING, <hi>and Conſequently of the Devil. And the Old</hi> Quakers <hi>have not yet Anſwered their Arguments, that I can hear of.</hi>
                  </q> Then it is high time it be done now, which I will perform by-and-by, but I muſt take my turn to ask <hi>Charles</hi> two Queſtions; to which he ſhall true Anſwer make, in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as he has before made the Old <hi>Quakers:</hi> My firſt is:</p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:44459:23"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Charles,</hi> Art thou <hi>a Child of Wrath?</hi> He muſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, <hi>Yea;</hi> or go againſt his own Avowed <hi>Principles.</hi> And if <hi>Yea;</hi> then the Text is plain againſt his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heriting <hi>the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi> This is very hard, a Man ſhould ſend himſelf thus to Hell; but don't Wonder, till we ſee what the next Queſtion will do.</p>
               <p>Let me ask again, <hi>Charles,</hi> Art thou a Diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient Son? He will ſay, <hi>Nay:</hi> For that is the common Epithet by which he deſcribes the Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient; and is a Term that he puts in Oppoſition to <hi>Loyalty,</hi> which he puts upon <hi>himſelf.</hi> Now it is written, <hi>Diſobedience is as the Sin of Witchcraft.</hi> Therefore, ſay all good Men, Diſobedience is a Wicked thing, and conſequently of the Devil. Now Reader ſee, Before he ſent himſelf, and now he would hale all the People thither: Thus the Vanity and Folly of his Idle Queſtions does appear; when by only turning the Tables, and ſhifting the Terms, they do as certainly Damn him, as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude againſt us. But now I come more cloſely to examine and ſee how his Extravagant Conſequences can be the Natural Reſult of our <hi>Common Principle, and Notion of the Light Within:</hi> We, according to the Holy Scriptures, ſay, <hi>That the Grace of God, which bringeth Salvation, appeareth unto all Men;</hi> and that the Grace, Light, Spirit, or Truth, (by all which, and more Names, it is called in Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) if obeyed in its Operation, will of Sinners make Saints: And when Men, by the Grace of God, are thus made Holy, they are then Partakers of him who is the <hi>firſt Reſurrection;</hi> for whereas they <hi>were Dead in Sins,</hi> they are now, by the Grace of God, <hi>made Alive unto Righteouſneſs,</hi> and ſo can then truly
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:44459:24"/> ſay with the Holy Apoſtle, <hi>How can we that ar dead to Sin, live any longer therein?</hi> And when Men are thus riſen from the Grave of Sin, and made alive unto Righteouſneſs, they then are truly capable of ſo enjoying Marriage, and all the other Comforts of this Life, as to Glorifie God, through Jeſus Chriſt, for that he hath made them Witneſſes of him who is the firſt Reſurrection, and Partakers of theſe his Temporal Mercies. As for the Terms of <hi>Children of the Light,</hi> and <hi>Children of the World,</hi> they are ſuch as it ſeemed good to our <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and his Apoſtles, frequently to uſe, as having in them a Significancy of Expreſſion, to denote the <hi>Wicked</hi> and the <hi>Godly,</hi> which is Authority ſufficient for us to uſe them in their proper places: And it is Eternally true, That Men, by Believing in the Light, (notwithſtanding his Idle Scoff) may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Children of the Light: And it is of neceſſity, that them that are truly ſuch, muſt be Separate from, and Diſcerners of, the Children of this World, <hi>i. e.</hi> Darkneſs; and not ſo only, but as they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in that Light of Chriſt Jeſus, wherewith he hath enlightned them, it will ſo <hi>renew the Spirit of their Minds,</hi> as both to let them ſee their Duty, and alſo enable them to do it; for it is no <hi>Ignis faiuus,</hi> no wild Enthuſiaſm, it leads not into Idle or Falſe Imaginations or Whimſies, but is Solid Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, and a true Guide to all Chriſtian Actions, and ſuch as become the Profeſſion thereof; And the Deduction and Conſequence is very plain, That when, by the Grace of God, Mens Underſtandings are Illumin'd, their Wills made Obedient, their Paſſions Subdued, and their Affections made Clean and Temperate, then the Actions of the Whole Man will be very Regular, and ſuch an one muſt
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:44459:24"/> needs be a good Chriſtian, a good Subject, a good Servant, a good Husband or Parent, and a good Neighbour: Governours will be Safe, Subjects Peaceable, Relations Affectionate, all Men love one another, and God from all, who over all is Bleſſed for ever, will receive Praiſe and Thankſgiving.</p>
               <p>Now our Practiſe, in the caſe of Marriage, is ſo well known, that little need be ſaid concerning it, only thus much I may ſay, that no Lawful Cauſes appearing to hinder, we never diſcourage Marriage; but when any ſuch do appear, it is agreeable to our Chriſtian Profeſſion to prevent them. The Method we have in this Caſe of Marriage, hath been laid before Men in Government, and hath by them been approved as ſuch, that will anſwer the End pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, that is, the Honour of Religion, and Peace and Safety of Civil Society, and Particular Perſons and Families: And beyond this I know of no Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion can be made, in the Adminiſtration of Church-Diſcipline. And if any after-Marriage, do break Wedlock, do become Vicious, <hi>and turn from the Grace of God into Wantonneſs,</hi> and do commit For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, it cannot be chargeable upon that Grace and Light, which had they kept obedient to, would have preſerved them; nor upon that Diſcipline, which, while they continue within our Society, is an abſolute Hedge againſt ſuch Diſorder. From all which, I ſuppoſe it may by this time appear, that our <hi>Common Principle and Notion of the Light Within,</hi> is no more chargeable with Back ſliders Faults, than with his Falſities.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:44459:25"/>
               <head>SECT. VI.</head>
               <p>HItherto his Perverſions and Malice have been manifeſt; I now come to his Sixth Point or Charge, <hi>That we Contemn Magiſtracy and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> His firſt Quotations are from himſelf in the Snake, and therefore of no notice to me here. What I firſt ſhall take notice of, is a pieced Quota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion he brings, out of <hi>George Fox</hi> in his <hi>Great Myſtery,</hi> Printed 1659. p. 76. and here I find the firſt Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence his Pen light on he cut aſunder, the place is thus, <hi>The Power of God</hi> (what follows he cut off) <hi>Rules and Orders People, when there is no outward Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. Nay, it</hi> (theſe two words he cut off) <hi>ſtrikes down Government of Men and Governours,</hi> (all that follows he left out) <hi>as in the days of</hi> Daniel <hi>and</hi> Pharaoh, <hi>and in many other places in Scripture mentioned.</hi> Now Reader, Can any Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Inquiſition be more careful to Expugn Paſſages offenſive to Chriſtian Eyes, than this Man is to Expugn ſuch as are offenſive to his own? The remaining part of the Quotation, he hath pick'd and pieced out of page 90. and by his diſlo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating and pulling aſunder the Sentences one from another, ſome of them look with as wry Faces, as if tortured in a Scotch Boot. I will at leaſt reſcue one of them, that we may ſee its Native Feature, the place being thus, <hi>Such as are turned into Corruption, and are Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Great Myſt.</hi> p. 90.</note> 
                  <hi>they are gone from the Higher Power which the Soul ſhould be ſubject to, and it's gone over them; and ſo</hi> (here he is pleaſed to begin) <hi>for the Lord's ſake the Saints cannot be ſubject to that</hi>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:44459:25"/> 
                  <hi>Power.</hi> By the remaining Sentences he has done the like, ſo that there is not one of them that ſpeaks the Mind of the Writer: The place is too long to tranſcribe here, becauſe I have many Inſtances to bring, where it will appear, that we always, ſince a People, have been Obedient to Government and Governours; and that, not for Fear but Conſcience ſake; and have always teſtified againſt Plotting and Contriving the Hurt or Ruin of any; which by our agreeable Practice, is better Proof for us, than all his own Lies, or the, by him, Suborned Paſſages, of our Writings, are againſt us.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Some Teſtimonies concerning our Acknowledgment of, and our Obedience to Government.</head>
                  <p>P. 10. <q rend="inline"> And the Powers that are ordained of God, who are <note place="margin">
                           <hi>The Path of the Juſt Cleared, 1655. By</hi> G. Whitehead, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        </note> ſent of him for the Puniſhment of Tranſgreſſors, and for the Encouragement of them that do well: Theſe we own, and are ſubject to them for Conſcience-ſake, knowing that ſuch <hi>are not a Terror to Good Works, but to Evil;</hi> for ſuch execute the Law in Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, upon them who are guilty of the Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion of it; for becauſe of Tranſgreſſion the Law is added, and there the Law is executed in its place, and in Righteouſneſs; and thoſe that execute the Law in its place, they are for the Eſtabliſhment of Righteouſneſs and Peace; and, contrary to the Law of Juſtice and Equity dare not Act in their own Wills, nor for their own Ends: And herein they ſeek not themſelves, nor their own Glory, nor Honour, but the Glory and
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:44459:26"/> Honour of God, who is Honoured and Glorified among them who Act in Truth and Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and love the Lord; and to them our Souls are ſubject. </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>P. 23. <q rend="inline"> And as for this <hi>preſent Authority</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> now in <note place="margin">
                           <hi>A Viſitation of Love, 1661. By</hi> Edw. Burroughs.</note> Being, under the Name of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, we do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve and acknowledge, That according to the Purpoſe and Will of God, and of his bringing to paſs, this preſent Government and Authority is ſet up, and, into its preſent being, eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed. </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>P 6. 7. <q rend="inline"> The Honour that is due unto Magiſtrates conſiſts in <note place="margin">
                           <hi>True Magiſtracy Deſcribed, 1660. By</hi> Henry Clark.</note> theſe two Particulars: 1. Love. <hi>2dly,</hi> Obedience. </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <q>
                        <hi> Firſt,</hi> He that is in the Well-doing himſelf, loves the Rulers that be ſet up of God, who are Juſt, and Rule in the Fear of God, and is a Terror to the Evil-doers; for <hi>When the Righteous are in Authority, the Children of Wiſdom rejoyce,</hi> deſiring of God that long they may Live, and Proſper in the Work of the Lord; and Love thinketh no Evil, nor behaveth not it ſelf unſeemly toward the Rulers, neither ſpeaketh any Evil againſt him, neither doth it revile the Judges. </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <q>
                        <hi> Secondly,</hi> Honour due to the Magiſtrate conſiſteth in Obedience, either Actively in Doing, or Paſſive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by a Willing, Patient, and Meek Suffering un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them for the Lord's ſake. </q>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:44459:26"/>
                  <p>
                     <q> And becauſe Chriſt's Headſhip, Kingſhip and Supremacy alone, <note place="margin">Sam. Fiſher, p. 34. <hi>of his Works.</hi>
                        </note> we (together with the <hi>True Church</hi> which is in God the Father, and in <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> the Light) can own in the Court of Conſcience, and in Matters purely Spiritual, and of meer Religious and Soul Concernment, and not any meer Mans (much leſs the Pope's or any Prieſts in ſuch Sacred Secrets) therefore are we miſtaken and miſranked among ſuch as are utter Enemies to the preſent <hi>King's Supremacy</hi> in theſe <hi>Dominions.</hi> Whereby we do, according to what the Spirit requires of us, in all Civil Cauſes and Caſes between Man and Man, ſubmit our ſelves to every Ordinance of Man himſelf (I ſay, in ſuch caſes) even for the Lord's ſake, whether unto the King, as Supream, or to ſuch as are ſent of him to be a Terror to Evil-doers, and a Praiſe to them that do well. And if thoſe who have the Sword in hand, ſhall turn it againſt us for well doing, and ſo act againſt the good Will of God, or impoſe, by God's Permiſſion, upon us, contrary to our Conſciences, even there where we cannot obey actively, we are willing to bear Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently, without Violent Reſiſtance, what God will leave us to Suffer from the Hands of ſuch as ſhould Protect us, not Reviling, nor Threatning, nor Curſing, but committing our Caſe in Quietneſs, to him that Judgeth Righteouſly, and our Souls to him in Well-doing: And that Paſſive Deportment muſt be, and is Judged by all, to be Equivolent to that Active Obedience, which others yield, for Fear, to what Laws ſoever is made among Men. </q>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:44459:27"/>
                  <p>Page 20. <q rend="inline"> Our Principle is, to bring all into a Peaceable Life, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>To the King and both Houſes of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, a Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,</hi> &amp;c. 1666. <hi>By</hi> John Whitehead Alex. Parker, <hi>and</hi> Leonard Fell.</note> out of thoſe things that are Evil, that the Law of God, and every Law of Man, that is grounded upon Reaſon and Equity, takes hold upon, and therein we are one with Juſtice. Therefore di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh between thoſe whoſe Principles lead to Violence, or other Evils, that the Law of God (and of Man, which is equal) takes hold upon; and us, who are one with Juſtice, and lead from thoſe things into a Peaceable Life, as much as in us lyes, with all Men, which is according to the Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of the Primitive Chriſtians. </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Page 101. <q rend="inline"> And thoſe Rulers, Governours or Magiſtrates, who <note place="margin">
                           <hi>The Life of God,</hi> &amp;c. 1677. <hi>By</hi> William Gibſon.</note> are a Terror to Evil Doers, and a Praiſe to thoſe that do well, are worthy of Honour, yea, of double Honour, and all ſuch are duly honoured by us, with the Honour which belongs unto them; and we really, and with Pleaſure, Honour and Obey all ſuch, not for fear of the Wrath, but for good Conſcience, ſake, as the Apoſtles and Primitive Fathers did. </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Page 481. <q rend="inline"> It is our Principle, and Teſtimony, to deny and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce <note place="margin">G. Fox's <hi>Journal given the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> 1680.</note> all Plots and Plotters againſt the King, or any of his Subjects, for we have the Spirit of Chriſt, by which we have the Mind of Chriſt, who came to Save Mens Lives, and not to Deſtroy them; and we </q>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:44459:27"/> would have the Kind, and all his Subjects, to be ſafe. Wherefore we do Declare, That we will Endeavour, to our Power, to Save and Defend him and them, by Diſcovering all Plots and Plotters (which ſhall come to our Knowledge) that would Deſtroy the King or his Subjects.</p>
                  <p>Theſe Quotations are, I hope, ſufficient for the purpoſe Intended; which is, To Teſtifie our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Peaceable Principle and Practice, in Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to Government and Magiſtracy; yet as a cloſe to all the foregoing Quotations from our Friends Books, I will give one Quotation, which Relates to near all the foregoing Charges, and which is taken from a Paper lately given to the Parliament, Occaſioned by <hi>E. Bugg's</hi> Calumnies; it's Entituled, <hi>The Quakers Vindication;</hi> and was PRESENTED to the Members of Parliament in <hi>December,</hi> 1693.</p>
                  <p>We whoſe Names are Under-written (being in Chriſtian Society with the People called <hi>Quakers)</hi> do, in good Conſcience, Declare and Certifie all Perſons Concerned.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That we ſincerely Believe and Confeſs, That <hi>Jeſus</hi> of <hi>Nazareth,</hi> who was Born of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> is the True <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> the very <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the Son of the Living God, to whom all the Prophets gave Witneſs. And we do Highly Value his Death, Sufferings, Works, Offices, and Merits for the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption and Salvation of Mankind, together with his Laws, Doctrine and Miniſtry.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That this very <hi>Chriſt</hi> of God, was and is the <hi>Lamb</hi> of God that takes away the Sins of the World, who was Slain, was Dead, and is Alive,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:44459:28"/> and Lives for Evermore, in his Divine Eternal Glory, Dominion and Power with the Father.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. That the Holy <hi>Scriptures</hi> of the Old and New Teſtament, are of <hi>Divine Authority,</hi> as being given by Inſpiration of God.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. And that <hi>Magiſtracy,</hi> or Civil <hi>Government,</hi> is God's Ordinance, the Good Ends thereof being for the Puniſhment of Evil Doers, and Praiſe of them that do Well.</p>
                  <p>And we know of no other Doctrine or Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple Preached, Maintained, or ever received among (or by) us, ſince we were a People, contrary to theſe aforeſaid</p>
                  <list>
                     <head>Signed in Behalf of the ſaid People.</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Thomas Lower</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>William Crouch</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>William Ingram</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>William Mead</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>William Macket</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Philip Ford</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Francis Camfield</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Edge</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Thomas Hudſon</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Charles Marſhall</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Joſiah Ellis</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Gilbert Latey</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Theodor Eccleſton</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Joſeph Waſey</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Thomas Cox</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Bowater</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>William Phillips</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Edward Brook</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>William Townſend</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Hall</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>George Oldner</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Thomas Barker</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Abraham Johnſon</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Thomas Twinbarrow</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Michael Ruſſell</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Harwood</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Danſon</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Stringfellow</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>William Paul</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Francis Eteridge</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Benjamin Bealing.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:44459:28"/>
                  <p>By what hath now been ſaid, and ſhewn, it may plainly appear, that his Charges are utterly Falſe; and notwithſtanding he makes Quotations, Page 16, 17. which he calls <hi>Edw. Burroughs's,</hi> to Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance his Villany herein; yet he is as far from Honeſty in his Quotation, as he is from Truth in all thoſe; for I ſhall ſhew that he hath Commited Forgery to make this Man's Writings anſwer his Mind. Part of his Quotation is thus, <hi>And Curſed be every one that riſeth not up to the Help of the Lord, againſt the Mighty. Put on your Armour,</hi> &amp;c. This, one would think, looks ſome-what with a Martial Face; but when, for Confirmation, I came to look in this Piece, called, <hi>The Camp of the Lord,</hi> whence he took theſe Lines, inſtead of finding them in the Order they now ſtand, the firſt Sentence is laſt, and both Twenty Three, or more, Lines aſunder, and the reſt of the Quotation he has alſo Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſed the Sentences, that they cannot ſpeak their Writer's Mind: How far this Practiee is, To Fight for <hi>the Joy and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion of</hi> Chriſtendom, <hi>and the Glory of God,</hi> is eaſie to find; it being an Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, for which the Inquiſition will hardly afford him Preſident, and a Practice that Glorifies not God, nor Advances the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> of <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> nor the <hi>Joy</hi> of any, but Men of Corrupt Minds: Beſides, this Piece of <hi>Edw. Burroughs,</hi> has not in it any Tendency to Outward War; the whole Piece, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an Allegory of the Chriſtian Spiritual War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare, which he Encourages his Brethren to go in; and if, where Divine Matters are thus ſpoken of, both in the Old and New Teſtament, the Places ſhould be thus Tortured, and the Sentences Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſed, they would not ſpeak in the Quieteſt Terms? Nay, our Lord's Prayer, if this Man had
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:44459:29"/> the turning the Sentences, he would ſoon ſpoil its Divine Authority.</p>
                  <p>But, that I might do Juſtice to the Memory of this our Deceaſed Friend, I have, among the Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations Relating to our Obedience to Magiſtracy and Government, given One from himſelf, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he is ſo full, plain and diſtinct, as may Effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally Vindicate his Memory, and our Principle. In like manner he hath Abuſed <hi>Samuel Fiſher,</hi> who, by the Quotation taken from him, will anſwer for himſelf.</p>
                  <p>I come now to the laſt Ridiculous Charge, of not pulling off our Hats, and giving Civil Titles, which he Falſly and Fooliſhly Inſinuates to have been Condemned by the Apoſtles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which is a Pretence ſo Idle, that he may as ſoon find in them Early Times, the taking of Snuff after his manner, to be declared Hereſie. But however, by his Title Page, we are to expect ſome <hi>Ancient Father</hi> to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn us. And when in Page 17. I found that Name, under the Prejudice of whoſe Cenſure the Snake had Plac'd us, I found it to be neither Father of the Church, nor Member of the Senhadrim, but <hi>Joſephus</hi> the Warlike-Jew; who, tho' he Profeſſes to Write the Wars of the Jews, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Pretended to Declare Hereſies: But this Man, that he might ſhew himſelf to be fully Qualified for the Inquiſition, can as eaſily Canonize this Jew, as Diſmember our Books. Well, I will not yet wholly reject <hi>Joſephus,</hi> but will Conſider the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance taken out of him, and which is <hi>Judas Gali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leu</hi>'s; Who (as he Quotes <hi>Joſephus,</hi> and I hope has been Honeſt here, tho' otherwiſe in our Books) <hi>would rather Expoſe themſelves, their Children and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, to the moſt Cruel Torments, than call any Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:44459:29"/> Man</hi> Lord <hi>or</hi> Maſter. Now, Believe me, Friends, I cannot ſee the Hereſie of this Doctrine, unleſs I ſhould Conclude, that to agree with <hi>Judas Galilaeus,</hi> in any thing were ſo; and if that be Rule to Judge by, I ſuppoſe this Snake is a Heretick too; for this Jew believed in One God, and if this Snake does not believe as much, he believes leſs than the Devil.</p>
                  <p>But beſides this Queſtion of <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Maſter,</hi> he has not given us any Apoſtle or Ancient Father to Condemn the Uſe of the Singular Number to a ſingle Perſon, or to Authorize the Uſe of the Plural in the ſame Caſe; nor has he yet Produced the like Authority to Reprove our <hi>Stiffneſs in not pulling off our Hats.</hi> If he meets with no ſuch Authority, nor finds any other <hi>Original Heretick,</hi> the Snake falls ſhort of Proof, both for Precedent and Cenſure; and then <hi>Geo. Fox</hi> has (in his own Fooliſh and Falſe Words) <hi>the Glory of being an Original.</hi> But now he affirms, that <hi>George Fox</hi>'s <hi>Inſpirations</hi> came from the <hi>Spirit of Pride;</hi> but how <hi>Charles</hi> will aſſure any Man of that, which he is not Infallibly Aſſured of himſelf (an Inſpiration, ſo foul a Veſſel muſt not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to) cannot readily be gueſſed. I come now to Examine, by Holy Scriptures, how far <hi>G. Fox</hi>'s Practice herein did, and ours does, agree there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with; for if it be agreeable with them, we ſhall not be careful for the reſt. Firſt, The Single Number, to a ſingle Perſon, in all the Inſtances the World hath yet had (that I know of) it hath ever been the Language of God and Angels unto Men, and the Language in Holy Writ of Holy Men to God, to Princes, to Rulers, and one unto another; which, without the Snake's leave, is Authority ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient for us; though, were I minded to be Prolix,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:44459:30"/> I could multiply Inſtances about the Reformation and in other times. And as for the Titles of <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Maſter;</hi> where, in the Scriptures they are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied and forbid, there and in ſuch Caſes we do deny and forbid them: And as for our Hats, we pull them not off in Ceremony or Civility, yet we pay Honour to whom Honour is due, Fear to whom Fear is due, and Civility to all Men with whom we Converſe; and this is agreeable to our Chriſtian Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion and Principles, which teaches us to preſerve and keep that Diſtinction and Order, in Perſons and Things, as is neceſſary for their Good Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Preſervation, which are the Good Ends we chiefly Deſire to aim at herein.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>CONCLVSION.</head>
               <p>I Have herein purpoſely omitted to ſay any thing to his Quotations of the Fathers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> becauſe, by what is before written, it appears, the Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons he ſets them againſt, are not ours; and that our Principles before-mentioned, are Conſonant to the Holy Scriptures, and not deſerving the ugly Shapes which this Snake endeavours to draw over them: For they are no other than the Doctrines which our Lord Jeſus Chriſt did reveal, and which his Apoſtles did Preach, and which after a time of great Apoſtacy have been again Preached, and by a Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Belief whereof, in Obedience to Chriſt Jeſus, Men may be enabled to diſtinguiſh between Light and Darkneſs: And notwithſtanding they have been, and are, withſtood by Men of Corrupt Minds, who would pervert the Way of the Upright, who cover
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:44459:30"/> themſelves with all Deceiveableneſs of Unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, yet they muſt Thrive and Proſper, for God hath Promiſed, <hi>He will Eſtabliſh Truth in the Earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And though this Man pretends to ſay, that we now begin to Complain of Miſrepreſention, it is wrong; for it is what we have had cauſe to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of, and what we have Complained of from Truths, and our Enemies from the firſt. And tho' every Adverſary, in their turn, may not have been ſo Violently Baſe, in ſlitting Sentences, and Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing them, and taking one part of our Words, and leaving out others Explanatory, as this Man has been, as is here before ſhewn and proved; yet we have had occaſion ſufficient to ſhew, wherein we have been Miſrepreſented by our Adverſaries; which yet hath often had this good Effect, that many, <hi>Berean</hi>-like, have applied themſelves to ſee whether thoſe things were ſo or no; and finding their Charges Falſe, have been drawn to Love and Eſpouſe that Truth, which hath been thus al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt <hi>every where ſpoken againſt,</hi> and to Worſhip God in <hi>that Way which ſome call Hereſie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now Jeſus Chriſt the Truth, and the Light which comes by him, hath, ſince we have been a People, been always Teſtified to by us, as that which is the only True Guide of Men, in matters Eternal, and of Soul Concernment, and do continue to be ſo Preached and Teſtified of; of which the few fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going Inſtances are proof; and that we are not changed. And we have and do continue to ſay, That whoever ſets up any other Guide, in Oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to this Truth and Light of Jeſus Chriſt, or prefers any other thing before it, they have not a right Ground of Faith, but all that are Obedient to this certain and right Ground of Faith, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:44459:31"/> to the Degree manifeſted unto them, we really own, by what Name ſoever called: And the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of our Friendſhip and true Communion in Spiritual Matters, is according to this Rule, and againſt it we cannot make Compoſition, becauſe we know by good Authority and Experience, <hi>whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is reprovable, is made manifeſt by the Light.</hi> And though it is poſſible for <hi>this Snake in the Graſs</hi> to imitate an Explanation of the Light within, and for the Devil to transform himſelf into an Angel of Light; yet they can no more be ſaid to be guided by the Light, than the Devil might be ſaid to be Refreſhed by the Sweets of Paradiſe, when he came to Deſtroy them: Nor can they that abide in the Light, have any Union at all with the Unfruitful Works of Darkneſs.</p>
               <p>By the Title and Contents of his Charge, this <hi>Snake</hi> would ſuggeſt us to Hereticks, but now in the Concluſion he ſoftens the Term, and brings it down to <hi>Separation,</hi> which he would not have kept up; by which he ſeems to arrogate the Title of <hi>Mediator,</hi> which Quality cannot be well performed, but by one admitted on both ſides, which this <hi>Snake</hi> is ſo far from being, that I may affirm, he is cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen by neither; for I can have no ground to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, That a Rebellious Son (whatſoever he may be for a Subject) can be dignified with Credentials to mediate her Cauſe whoſe Head he hath denied; and I am very ſure, that we ſhall never chuſe him for Mediator, who, we find, is diſpoſed to ſay any thing of us, rather than what is right; and ſeems to have the reverſe of that Quality which <hi>Midas</hi> is Fabled to have had, of turning all he touch'd into Gold, for what of ours this Man's Pen touches, he commonly turns it to Poyſon.</p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:44459:31"/>
               <p>As for what reſpects our nearneſs of Belief with the other Communities of Men in the Nation, I am ſo far from being Sorry that others acknowledge the Light of <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> that I hope I ſhall always rejoyce in it, and in a Life obedient to it; into which Obedience, as the whole Nation comes, their Separations will be leſs, and their Union more and greater, under that one Eternal Head, <hi>Who by one Offering hath per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 10. 14, 15.</note> 
                  <hi>for ever them that are ſanctified: Whereof alſo the Holy Ghoſt is a Witneſs to us.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The Expoſtulation with</hi> W. Penn <hi>Conſidered.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>I Have before ſhewed, that our Principles are now no other than what they were when firſt a People, and that they are confonant to the Holy Scriptures; ſo that that Book of <hi>William Penn's,</hi> Entituled, <hi>Primitive Chriſtianity,</hi> &amp;c. is no new Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation, concerning which Book ſomewhat is now to be ſaid, at leaſt to places quoted and cavilled at by this <hi>Snake,</hi> and he firſt quotes p. 29. and ſays, W. Penn <hi>will not grant we have any Natural Light at all;</hi> which is an Abuſe and Perverſion; for <hi>W. Penn</hi> denies not Natural Light to Men, but that by it they can underſtand the things of God, is what <hi>W. Penn</hi> in that place ſpeaks of; and this is agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Apoſtle, who hath told us, That the things of God are not to be known, but by the Spirit of God.</p>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:44459:32"/>
                  <p>He next turns to <hi>George Fox's Great Myſtery,</hi> p. 42. where he as plainly perverts the Sence of this place, as the laſt, for the Tenet oppoſed by <hi>George Fox</hi> was, <hi>That no Man, by that Native Light inherent in him, had power to believe:</hi> And <hi>G. Fox</hi> had reaſon to oppoſe this Tenet, becauſe it appears p. 39. <hi>Great Myſtery,</hi> what his Adverſary did mean by <hi>Native</hi> and <hi>Inherent</hi> Light, <hi>viz.</hi> That Light wherewith every one that cometh into the World is enlightned withall. This was what <hi>George Fox</hi> did preach, and which the Prieſt did oppoſe, and therefore <hi>G. Fox</hi> anſwers it with the Text of <hi>John</hi> 1. 9. and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes from it (and that very truly) that this Light <hi>is beyond Natural Senſe and Reaſon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>He returns again to <hi>W. Penn's Prim. Chriſ.</hi> p. 15. where he ſays, W. Penn <hi>allows no Natural Light to the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding;</hi> which is a manifeſt Perverſion of the place, the words alledged are, <hi>Man can no more be a Light to his Mind, than he can to his Body.</hi> But if this Man had been ſo Honeſt, as to have alſo tranſcribed out of the ſame Paragraph theſe words, viz. <hi>About thoſe things that more immediately concern our Better, Inward and Eternal Man;</hi> he would have found his Cavil uſeleſs, and his Flout would have appeared as flat, as now his Charge appears Falſe, and he may take his grains of Allowance again. The <hi>Snake</hi> leaps from p. 15 to 50, and here thinks fit to carp and bite at this Expreſſion, <hi>All Men have Reaſon, but all are not Reaſonable:</hi> Where's the Riddle, Jeſt or Nonſence of this Paſſage, Men have Reaſon, <hi>in potentia,</hi> but if they will not uſe it the Fault is their own; this <hi>W. Penn</hi> further ſpeaks to in p. 51. his words are, <hi>For the reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able part of Man, is his Spiritual part, and that guided by the Divine <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, or Word, which</hi> Tertullian <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprets,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:44459:32"/> Reaſon in the moſt Excellent Senſe, makes Man truly reaſonable; and then it is that Man comes to offer up himſelf to God a Reaſonable Sacrifice.</hi> In what plainer words can a Man own Man's Reaſon, and God's Revelation, the firſt as it is Natural, and the other as it is Divine.</p>
                  <p>He leaves <hi>W. Penn</hi> at preſent, and turns to <hi>Edw. Burroughs</hi> p. 17. of his Works, from whence he makes a Quotation, but hath abuſed the Sence of the place, by leaving out the two following Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, and then the place is thus. <hi>I wrote not as from Man, whoſe Light is</hi> ONLY <hi>Natural and Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, and doth</hi> ONLY <hi>make manifeſt Carnal Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, of a Carnal Law, but as from the Eternal and Spiritual Light, which doth make manifeſt Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Tranſgreſſions of a Spiritual Law.</hi> From this place <hi>John Stalham</hi> would faſtly conclude, that <hi>Edw. Burroughs</hi> called the Light of Chriſt Carnal, which, that he did not, I think is very plain: And accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly <hi>Richard Hubberthorn</hi> p. 144. ſays, That we do not allow any to call the Light of Chriſt Jeſus Natural, but <hi>the Light of Man, by which Carnal Men do judge of Carnal Tranſgreſſions.</hi> So that <hi>W. Penn,</hi> and both theſe, do allow the Natural Reaſon, or Light of Man, to be one thing, and the Divine Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Holy Spirit another; ſo that they do all plainly agree, in the One Holy Spirit, or Light of Chriſt Jeſus, given in meaſure to all Men to guide them; and this <hi>W. Penn</hi> hath not oppoſed, nor the reaſonable Underſtanding of Man, as this would falſly ſuggeſt.</p>
                  <p>He comes back to p. 29. where he would have <hi>W. Penn</hi> to <hi>Suppoſe, that nothing, but the Divine Light, could reprove of Evil.</hi> But I have look'd, and find no ſuch Suppoſition, and therefore no further notice
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:44459:33"/> need be taken of the Conſequences he draws as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending on that Suppoſition. Yet nevertheleſs I may add; That as no one knows the things of God, but by the Spirit of God; ſo if Man do at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend upon the Manifeſtation of this Holy Spirit, it will diſcover to him all that is Reproveable; and without which, by any reaſon of his own, he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not make ſuch Diſcovery; and by its Power it can, and if Man be Obedient, it will enable him to turn from that which it does ſo Diſcover and Reprove him for: This is that ſure Baſis, upon which, being fixed, we eaſily reject all Guileful Pretences to the contrary: And tho' this Man may have a great Opinion of his Wiſe Charming, p. 24. yet I never underſtood that the Hiſſing of a Snake was Wiſe Charming.</p>
                  <p>Now if any go from the Spirit of God into De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſions; is that reaſon ſufficient why none ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon the Guidance of the Spirit of God. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, there have been innumerable Falſly pretended Miracles, muſt we therefore believe no true Ones: No, the Effect it ought to have, ſhould be quite otherwiſe; have others by Diſobedience, and leaving of their Guide, fallen into Deluſion, let me there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore attend my Watch more cloſly; have others by forſaking their True Guide, the Holy Spirit, been given up to believe Lies; let me keep cloſe to it, that it be not ſo with me: But if inſtead of this, Men will pretend to ſubject the Unerring Spirit of God, to be tried by the Erring Spirit of Man, as it is not Scriptural, ſo neither is it ſafe; nay, it cannot be ſafe, if to the Spirit of Man, they add all Study, all meer Humane Endeavour, all Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, Ordinances, Hiſtories or Humane Learning, all theſe will not Poiſe the Ballance where the Spirit
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:44459:33"/> of God is wanting, nor can any of theſe perform that excellent Office of the <hi>Spirit of Truth,</hi> which our Saviour hath Infallibly Aſſured, <hi>will lead into all Truth;</hi> and when we have all Truth, what Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Good can we want. And this deſtroys not the <hi>Freedom of Man's Will,</hi> nor Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, nor <hi>extinguiſhes his Humane</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Page 26, 27.</note> 
                     <hi>Reaſon,</hi> but on the contrary, exalts and enobles all the Powers and Faculties of the Mind. So that it is utterly impoſſible for a Man, under the Guidance of the Spirit of Truth, to make God the Author of Sin: Nor does this Principle arraign the Wiſdom of God <hi>in his Ordinances,</hi> but ſhews forth his Good Will to Men, in that he has not only ſent forth the <hi>Spirit of Truth,</hi> but alſo ſends forth <hi>his Servants</hi> guided by it, to call the People into Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to it. And thus God is pleaſed to work me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately and immediately.</p>
                  <p>Here in p. 29. he would ſeem to approve and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratulate <hi>W. Penn</hi> upon his <hi>Expoſition of Juſtification,</hi> but his Aſſent or Diſſent we value not, nor our ſelves for its ſake; but the Doctrine is true, and hath from the firſt been profeſſed by us. But to remind him a little, How is it poſſible for us to be Orthodox herein (as he ſays we are) and Heretical in the Articles which relate to Chriſt Jeſus, as God and as Man, by and through whom Juſtification comes? But Self-contradiction is no new thing to this Man.</p>
                  <p>He now numbers up in Page 30, 31, 32. divers things, wherein he would fain have the Church and us agree, they not being ſufficient (as he ſays) for
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:44459:34"/> Separation. This Man is of a very changeable Humour, in his Title, and for near all the Book, we were Sad Hereticks, but now he would have us Aſſociates, which if we will not be, he gives a Threatning Advertiſement, that he will Trump up more Hereſies upon us. Well, in that let him do as God ſhall permit; but of two things he may be aſſured, that we ſhall have no Communion with his Lies, nor he true Peace in perſiſting in them.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:44459:34"/>
            <head>
               <hi>BOOKS Printed and Sold by</hi> T. Sowle, <hi>next to the</hi> Meeting-Houſe <hi>in</hi> White-Hart-Court, <hi>in</hi> Gracious-Street. <hi>And at the</hi> Bible <hi>in</hi> Leaden-Hall-Street, <hi>near the</hi> Market, 1697.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>SAmuel Fiſher</hi>'s Works, in <hi>Folio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Works of the Long, Mournful, and Sorrowful Diſtreſſed <hi>Iſaac Penington</hi>'s, <hi>Folio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>William Bayly</hi>'s Works, <hi>Quarto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Works of that Memorable and Ancient Servant of Chriſt <hi>Stephen Criſp;</hi> containing alſo a Journal of his Life, giving an Account of his Convincement, Travels, Labours, and Sufferings in, and for the Truth. Price Bound 5 s.</p>
            <p>A Collection of the ſeveral Writings and Faithful Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of that ſuffering Servant of God, and patient Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lower of the Lamb, <hi>Humphry Smith.</hi> Price Bound 2 s. 6 d.</p>
            <p>A Collection of certain Epiſtles and Teſtimonies of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Conſolation, Experience, and Doctrine; Written by that Faithful, Patient and Long-ſuffering Servant of Chriſt, <hi>William Bennit.</hi> Price Bound 1 s. 8 d.</p>
            <p>The Memory of the Righteous Revived, being a brief Collection of the Books and Written Epiſtles of <hi>John Camm</hi> and <hi>John Andland:</hi> Together with ſeveral Teſtimonies re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to thoſe two Faithful Labourers. Price Bound 2 s.</p>
            <p>Truth Vindicated, by the Faithful Teſtimony and Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of the Innocent Servant and Handmaid of the Lord, <hi>Elizabeth Bathurſt,</hi> Deceaſed. Price Bound 1 s.</p>
            <p>Baptiſm and the Lord's Supper, Subſtantially Aſſerted; being an Apology in behalf of the People called <hi>Quakers,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning thoſe Two Heads. By <hi>Robert Barclay.</hi> Price Bound 1 s.</p>
            <p>A Catechiſm and Confeſſion of Faith. By <hi>R. Barclay.</hi> Price Bound 9 d.</p>
            <p>No Croſs, No Crown. A Diſcourſe ſhewing the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Diſcipline of the Holy Croſs of Chriſt. By <hi>W. Penn.</hi> In Two Parts. The Fifth Edition. Price 3 s.</p>
            <p>An Addreſs to Proteſtants of all Perſwaſions; more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the Magiſtracy and Clergy, for the Promotion of Virtue and Charity. In Two Parts. By <hi>W. Penn,</hi> a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant.
<pb facs="tcp:44459:35"/> The Second Edition, Corrected and Enlarged. Price Bound 1 s. 6 d.</p>
            <p>An Account of <hi>W. Penn</hi>'s Travails in <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> for the Service of the Goſpel of Chriſt; by way of Journal. Containing alſo divers Letters and Epiſtles writ to ſeveral Great and Eminent Perſons whilſt there. The Second Impreſſion, Corrected by the Author's own Copy, with ſome Anſwers not before Printed. Price Bound 2 s.</p>
            <p>A Brief Account of the Riſe and Progreſs of the People called <hi>Quakers,</hi> in which their Fundamental Principle, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, Worſhip, Miniſtry and Diſcipline are plainly De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, to prevent the Miſtakes and Perverſions that Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance and Prejudice may make to abuſe the Credulous. With a Summary Relation of the former Diſpenſations of God in the World, by way of Introduction. By <hi>W. Penn.</hi> Price Bound 1 s.</p>
            <p>A Caſt to <hi>Chriſtendom.</hi> By <hi>W. Penn.</hi> Price Stich'd 3 d. Tender Counſel and Advice, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> By <hi>W. Penn.</hi> Price Stitch'd 3 d.</p>
            <p>The Harmony of Divine and Heavenly <hi>Doctrines,</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated in ſundry Declarations on Variety of Subjects. Preached at the <hi>Quakers</hi> Meetings in <hi>London,</hi> by Mr. <hi>W. Penn,</hi> Mr. <hi>G. Whitehead,</hi> Mr. <hi>S. Waldenfield,</hi> Mr. <hi>B. Coole,</hi> Taken in Short-hand as it was delivered by them; and now Faithfully Tranſcribed and Publiſhed for the Information of thoſe who by reaſon of Ignorance may have received a Prejudice againſt them. By a Lover of that People. Price 1 s. 6 d.</p>
            <p>Primitive Chriſtianity Revived, in the Faith and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of the People called <hi>Quakers.</hi> Written, in Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to the preſent Diſpenſation of God, through them to the World: That Prejudices may be Removed, the Simple In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, the Well-enclined Encouraged, and the Truth and its Innocent Friends Rightly Repreſented. By <hi>W. Penn.</hi> Price 1 s.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rabſhakeh</hi> Rebuked, and his Railing Accuſations Refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; containing, 1. Some Reflections upon a late Sheet, Entituled, <hi>An Eſſay towards the allaying of</hi> George Fox <hi>his Spirit;</hi> by way of Introduction. II. A Reply to a later Book, Entituled, <hi>A Diſcovery of the Accurſed Thing,</hi> &amp;c.
<pb facs="tcp:44459:35"/> 
               <hi>Enlarged;</hi> both written by <hi>Thomas Criſpe.</hi> III. A Diſplay of ſome, amongſt many, of his Self-contradictions and Tautologies; by way of Concluſion. By <hi>E. P.</hi> Price Stitch'd 6 d.</p>
            <p>A Diurnal Speculum; containing, I. A plain and eaſie Method to find out thoſe things that are moſt uſeful to be known Yearly: And may ſerve as an Almanack for Thirty Years; and many other things ſuitable to the Matter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> II. An Explanation of Weights, Money, and Meaſures, both Scriptural and Uſual, with ſundry Tables depending thereon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> III. Some Remarks on <hi>England;</hi> or a Brief Account of every County, with the Names, and Days of the Markets, and the Chief Commodities therein, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The whole conſiſting of Great Variety, explained by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Examples, the like in all particulars not extant; as by the Contents does more at large appear. Collected by <hi>J. B.</hi> Price Bound 1 s. 6 d.</p>
            <p>The Spirit of the Martyrs revived, in a breif Compendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Collection of the moſt Remarkable Paſſages and Living Teſtimonies of the True Church, Seed of God, and Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Martyrs in all Ages. Price 2 s. 6 d.</p>
            <p>The Arraignment of Popery: being a Collection taken out of the Chronicles and other Books of the State of the Church in the Primitive Times. I. The State of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts; how long it was before the Univerſal POPE and MASS was ſet up; and the bringing in their Rudiments. Traditions, Beads, Images, Purgatories, Tythes and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitions. II. A Relation of the Cruelties they acted after the Pope got up, being worſe than the <hi>Turk</hi> and <hi>Heathen: New Rome</hi> proving like <hi>Old.</hi> III. What the People of <hi>England</hi> Worſhipped before they were Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. IV. To which is added, the Blood of the Martyrs is the Seed of the Church. With ſeveral other things, very profitable for all that fear God to Read, Try and give Judgment by the Spirit of Truth, againſt the Worſhip of the Beaſt and Whore. Price 1 s. 6 d.</p>
            <p>Inſtructions for Right Spelling, and plain Directions for Reading and Writing True Engliſh. With ſeveral de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful things, very Uſeful and Neceſſary, both for Young and Old to Read and Learn. Price 6 d.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:44459:36"/>
            <p>A New Book for Children to Learn in. With many wholeſome Meditations for them to conſider. With Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections for true Spelling. And the Ground of true Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Writing of True Engliſh. Price 3 d.</p>
            <p>Miſcellania: Or a Collection of Neceſſary, Uſeful, and Profitable Tracts on variety of Subjects, which, for their Excellency, and Benefit of Mankind, are compiled in one Volumn. By <hi>Thomas Tryon</hi> Phyſiologus. Price 1 s.</p>
            <p>A Treatiſe of Charity; and as directed, Univerſal, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law, and under the Goſpel; (ſhewing the Nullity of all Religion without it) as alſo of Goodneſs, Providence; Riches, Poverty, Proſperity, and Adverſity. And of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificing and Feaſting, their continuance under the Goſpel. With a Paraphraſe upon the Parable of <hi>Dives</hi> and <hi>Lazarus.</hi> Price Bound 1 s.</p>
            <p>Antichriſt Unvailed, by the Finger of God's Power; and his Viſage Diſcovered by the Light of Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Written in the Love of God by a Priſoner (at <hi>Lancaſter</hi> Caſtle) for the Teſtimony of Truth, and one of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple called (in Scorn) <hi>Quakers.</hi> Price Bound 2 s.</p>
            <p>An Account of the Life and Death of our Faithful Friend and Fellow-labourer in the Goſpel, <hi>Thomas Markham;</hi> with ſeveral Teſtimonies concerning him, given forth by ſeveral Friends, whoſe Names are thereto Subſcribed. Alſoa Teſtimony written by himſelf, for the Neceſſity of Wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the Lord, and the Benefits thereof to Men: Where being Dead, he yet Speaketh. Price Stitch'd 4 d.</p>
            <p>Propoſal for raiſing a Colledge of Induſtry of all uſeful Trades and Husbandry, with Profit for the Rich. A Plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful Living for the Poor, and a good Education for Youth. Which will be Advantage to the Government, by the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of the People, and their Riches. Price 4 d.</p>
            <p>An Epiſtle to Friends; ſhewing, the Great Difference between a Convinced Eſtate and a Converted Eſtate; and between the Profeſſion of the Truth, and the Poſſeſſion thereof; with the Comfort and Sweetneſs to the Soul it af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fordeth. With a few Words of good Counſel and whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Advice to both Parents and their Children. Price 2 d</p>
            <p>The Counterfeit Convert, a Scandal to Chriſtianity, and his unjuſtly oppoſing Quakeriſm to Chriſtianity juſtly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended.
<pb facs="tcp:44459:36"/> And the True Chriſt, and Scriptures confeſſed by the Quakers. In Oppoſition to Two Scandalous Books falſly ſtiled, I. <hi>Quakeriſm Withered, and Chriſtianity Revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving.</hi> II. <hi>Animadverſions on</hi> G. Whitehead's <hi>Book,</hi> Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency Triumphant Price Stich'd 6 p.</p>
            <p>An Invitation, from the Spirit of Chriſt, to all that are a Thirſt, to come and Drink of the Waters of Life freely, which proceed from the Fountain of Eternal Life: ſhewing how all may come, that are willing, to Drink thereof to their full Satisfaction; whereby they may attain unto per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Health and Salvation of their Souls for ever in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt. And alſo, ſhewing what it is that hindereth People from being truly a Thirſt after the Waters of Life; and from coming to <hi>Drink</hi> thereof; with the deſtructive Quality of that which hindreth; and how it may be avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Concluded, with a Word to all Singers, upon a Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous or Spiritual Account. Written by one, who hath for a long time been deeply Diſtreſſed with Thirſt after the Water of Life; out, through Mercy, hath Obtained Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction thereby: Known by the Name of, <hi>Henry Mol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineux.</hi> Price Bound 1 s.</p>
            <p>The Spiritual Guide, which diſ-intangles the Soul, and brings it by the inward Way, to the getting of perfect Contemplation, and the Rich Treaſure of Internal Peace. Written by Dr. <hi>Michael de Molinos,</hi> Prieſt. Tranſlated from the <hi>Italian</hi> Copy. Price Bound 9 d.</p>
            <p>An Eſſay towards the Preſent and Future Peace of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi> by the Eſtabliſhment of an <hi>European</hi> Dyet, Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or Eſtates. Price Stitch'd 2 d.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Spira Reſpirans;</hi> or the Way to the Kingdom of Heaven, by the Gates of Hell; in an Extraordinary Example. By a Perſon brought to the depths of Deſpair and Anguiſh, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered by the mighty Grace and Power of God, and rais'd to the heights of Aſſurance and Joy. Wherein are ſome uncommon Conſiderations concerning the manner of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Damnation, Life and Death, Happineſs and Miſery. With ſome Fundamental Arguments for the Immortality of the Soul. Price Stitch'd 6 d.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:44459:37"/>
            <p>AN Epiſtle to Friends, briefly Commemorating the Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Dealings of the Lord with them; and warning them to beware of that Spirit of Contention and Diviſion which hath appeared of late in <hi>George Keith,</hi> and ſome few others that join with him, who have made a Breach and Separation from Friends in ſome Parts of <hi>America.</hi> By <hi>Thomas Ellwood.</hi> Price stitch'd 6 d.</p>
            <p>The State of the Caſe, briefly but impartially given, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the People called <hi>Quakers</hi> in <hi>Pennſylvania,</hi> &amp;c. in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merica,</hi> who remain in Unity; and <hi>George Keith,</hi> with ſome few Seduced by him into a Separation from them. As alſo a juſt Vindication of my Self from the Reproaches and Abuſes of thoſe Backſliders. By <hi>Samuel Jennings.</hi> Price Stitch'd 6 d.</p>
            <p>A Further Diſcovery of that Spirit of Contention and Diviſion which hath of late appeared in <hi>George Keith,</hi> &amp;c. Being a Reply to two late Printed Pieces of his, the one Entituled, <hi>A Loving Epiſtle,</hi> &amp;c: The other, <hi>A Seaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Information,</hi> &amp;c. Wherein his Cavils are anſwered, his Falſhood is laid open, and the Guilt and Blame of the Breach and Separation in <hi>America;</hi> and of the Reproach he hath brought upon Truth and Friends, by his late Printed Booke are fixed faſter on him. Written by way of Epiſtle, and Recommended as a further Warning to all Friends. By <hi>Thomas Ellwood.</hi> Price Stitch'd 1 s.</p>
            <p>Truth Defended, and the Friends thereof Cleared, from the falſe Charges, foul Reproaches, and envious Cavils, caſt upon It and Them, by <hi>George Keith</hi> (an Apoſtate from them) in two Books by him lately Publiſhed; the one being called, <hi>A True Copy of a Paper given into the Year<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Meeting of the People called</hi> Quakers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The other, <hi>The Pretended Yearly Meeting of the</hi> Quakers, <hi>their Nameleſs Bull of Excommunication,</hi> &amp;c. Both which Books are here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Anſwered, and his Malice, Injuſtice, and Folly, Expoſed, By <hi>Thomas Ellwood.</hi> Price Stitch'd 1 s.</p>
            <p>An Apoſtate Expoſed: Or, <hi>George Keith</hi> contradicting himſelf and his Brother <hi>Bradford;</hi> wherein their Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony to the Chriſtian Faith of the People called <hi>Quakers,</hi> is oppoſed to <hi>G. K</hi>'s late Pamphlet, Stiled, <hi>Groſs Error and Hypocrifie Detected.</hi> By <hi>John Penington.</hi> Price Stitch'd 3 d.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:44459:37"/>
            <p>A Modeſt Account from <hi>Pennſylvania</hi> of the Principal Differences in Point of Doctrine, between <hi>George Keith,</hi> and thoſe of the People called <hi>Quakers,</hi> from whom he ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated; ſhewing his great Deolenſion, and Inconſiſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy with himſelf therein. Recommended to the Serious Conſideration of thoſe who are turned aſide, and joined in his Schiſm. Price Stitch'd 4 d.</p>
            <p>The People called <hi>Quakers</hi> cleared by <hi>George Keith,</hi> from the falſe Doctrines charged upon them by <hi>G. Keith;</hi> and his Self-Contradictions laid open in the enſuing Citations out of his Books. By <hi>John Penington.</hi> Price Stitch'd 4 d.</p>
            <p>More Work for <hi>George Keith:</hi> Being <hi>George Keith's</hi> Vindication of the People called <hi>Quakers,</hi> as well in his Part of the Diſpute held at <hi>Wheelers-Street,</hi> the Sixteenth Day of the Eighth Month, 1674. As in his Treatiſe againſt <hi>Thomas Hicks,</hi> and other <hi>Baptiſts,</hi> with the reſt of their Confederate Brethren, at the <hi>Barbican</hi> Diſpute, held at <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> the twenty eighth of the Sixth Month, 1674. Price Stitch'd 4 d.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Quakers</hi> cleared from being Apoſtates: Or, the Hammerer Defeated, and proved on Impoſtor. Being an Anſwer to a Scurrilous Pamphlet, falſly Intituled, <hi>William Penn and the</hi> Quakers <hi>either Apoſtates or Impoſtors,</hi> ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed <hi>Trepidantium Malleus.</hi> With a Poſtſcript, containing ſome Roflections on a Pamphlet, Intituled, <hi>The Spirit of</hi> Quakeriſm, <hi>and the Danger of their</hi> Divine Revelation <hi>laid open.</hi> By <hi>B. C.</hi> Price Stitch'd 6 d.</p>
            <p>An Anſwer to <hi>George Keith's</hi> Narrative of his Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings at <hi>Turners-Hall,</hi> on the eleventh of the Month called <hi>June,</hi> 1696. Wherein his Charges againſt divers of the People called <hi>Quakers</hi> (both in that, and in another Book of his, called, <hi>Groſs Error and Hypocrifie Detected)</hi> are fairly Conſidered, Examined, and Refuted. By <hi>Thomas Ellwood.</hi> Prce 1 s. 6 d.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Keith</hi> againſt <hi>Keith:</hi> Or ſome more of <hi>George, Keith</hi>'s Contradictions and Abſurdities, collected out of his own Books (not yet Retracted.) upon a Review. Together with a Reply to <hi>George Keith</hi>'s Late Book, Entituled, <hi>The Antichriſts and Sadduces detected among a ſort of</hi> Quakers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> By <hi>John Penington.</hi> Price Stitch'd 9 d.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:44459:38"/>
            <p>Some Brief Obſervations upon <hi>George Keith's</hi> Earneſt, Expoſtulation, contained in a Poſtſcript to a late Book of his, Entituled, <hi>The Antichriſts and Sadduces Detected,</hi> &amp;c. Offered to the Peruſal of ſuch as the ſaid Expoſtulation was Recommended to. By <hi>E. P.</hi> Price Stitch'd 2 d.</p>
            <p>A Modeſt Detection of <hi>George Keith</hi>'s (miſcalled) Juſt Vindication of his Earneſt Expoſtulation: Publiſhed by him as a pretended Anſwer to a Late Book of Mine, Entituled, <hi>Some Brief Obſervations,</hi> &amp;c. By <hi>E. P.</hi> Price Stitch'd 4 d.</p>
            <p>A Few Queries relating to the Practice of Phyſick, with Remarks upon ſome of them. Modeſtly propoſed to the ſerious Conſideration of Mankind, in order to their Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation how their Lives and Healths, (which are ſo neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and therefore ought to be dear to them) may be better preſerved. By <hi>H. Chamberlen,</hi> Phyſician in Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary to the Late King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second. Price Bound 1 s.</p>
            <p>The Writing Scholar's Companion: Or, Infallible Rules for Writing True Engliſh with Eaſe and Certainty: Drawn from the Grounds and Reaſons of the Engliſh Tongue. Comprehending in a Full, Plain, and Exact Method, whatever is neceſſary to be obſerved in Writing True Engliſh. In Three Parts. Compoſed forthe Benefit of all ſuch as are Induſtriouſly Ambitious of ſo Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable an Ornament, as Writing true Engliſh is generally eſteemed. Recommended eſpecially to the Youth of both Sexes, and to be Taught in Schools. Price Bound 1 s.</p>
            <p>The Good Houſe-wife made a Doctor: Or, Health's Choice and Sure Friend. Being a plain way of Nature's own preſcribing, to prevent and Cure moſt Diſeaſes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident to Men, Women, and Children, by Diet and Kitchin-Phyſick only. With ſome Romarks on the Practice of Phyſick and Chymiſtry. By <hi>Thomas Tryon,</hi> Student in Phyſick. The Second Edition, To which is added ſome Obſervations on the Tedious Methods of Unskilful Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgions; with Cheap and Eaſie Remedies. By the ſame Author. Price Bound 1 s. 6 d.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
